<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sounding of the two last trumpets, the sixt and seventh or Meditations by way of paraphrase upon the 9th. 10th. and 11th. Chapters of the Revelation, as containing a prophecie of these last times. / Digested by Henry Burton during his banishment, and close imprisonment in the isle of Guernsey.</title>
            <author>Burton, Henry, 1578-1648.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 187 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78030</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B6172</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E174_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6165</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872951</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872951</idno>
            <idno type="VID">157070</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78030)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 157070)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 30:E174[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sounding of the two last trumpets, the sixt and seventh or Meditations by way of paraphrase upon the 9th. 10th. and 11th. Chapters of the Revelation, as containing a prophecie of these last times. / Digested by Henry Burton during his banishment, and close imprisonment in the isle of Guernsey.</title>
                  <author>Burton, Henry, 1578-1648.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 93, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Gellibrand at the Brazen Serpent in Pauls church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation IX-XI --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:157070:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:157070:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SOVNDING OF THE TWO LAST TRVMPETS, the ſixt and ſeventh: OR Meditations by way of Paraphraſe upon the 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. and 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Chapters of the REVELATION, as containing a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie of theſe laſt Times.</p>
            <p>Digeſted by <hi>Henry Burton</hi> during his Baniſhment, and cloſe impriſonment in the Iſle of <hi>GVERNSEY.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Revel. 1.11.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I heard a great voice as of a Trumpet, ſaying, what thou ſeeſt Write in a Book, and ſend it to the Churches.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for SAMUEL GELLIBRAND at the <hi>Brazen Serpent</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:157070:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:157070:2"/>
            <head>TO The Honourable the Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes of the Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> now aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt Noble &amp; grave Senate, having by me a certain <hi>Idea</hi> of ſome <hi>Meditations</hi> upon the ſounding of the <hi>ſixth Trumpet,</hi> which <hi>Idea</hi> I firſt conceived in my cloſe Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Exile, the wombe of its breeding, forming, and growing to that ſmall ſtature it is of: and finding (by comparing with this trumpets ſound, the ſight of thoſe remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things within the circuit of our times) ſuch an harmony between them, as the things themſelves ſeemed to returne a full eccho to the ſound; which as it afforded mee matter to exerciſe and recreate my thoughts, and ſo to deceive the naturall <hi>taedium</hi> of ſo horrid a ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarineſſe, and to ſupport humane infirmities with ſome hope, that it was not impoſsible
<pb facs="tcp:157070:3"/> (all circumſtances weighed) that ſuch a dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life (meerly upheld by a divine power) might yet ſurvive to bee an eye-witneſſe of the accompliſhment of the things then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning to be fulfilled: ſo now (though ſo long ſince my returne) I have conceived it might bee not altogether unſeaſonable for your godly wiſdomes to take notice of it, as who have no ſmall intereſt in it, ſeeing it hath pleaſed the Divine Providence in ſo full and important a ſeaſon to call you together to be the grand Agents and Inſtruments of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing his great worke falling with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſound of this <hi>Trumpet,</hi> and haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning on the terrible ſummons and conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the ſeventh and laſt: to whom then ſhould I now dedicate theſe my <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations</hi> but to your worthy ſelves, and that not only for the intereſt you have of right in them, but in me alſo, whoſe deliverance from Priſon and Exile, your unanimous votes made the handſell and firſt-fruits, and ſo the happy <hi>Auſpicia</hi> of this ever famous and unpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralleld Parliament? ſo as I have received, and doe enjoy a ſecond life, which under God I owe to the immaculate juſtice of this Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb facs="tcp:157070:3"/> Houſe; nor a life only, but (which is better then this life) a glorious libertie, and that not only from a perpetuall priſon and exile, but (with many thouſands more) from the bonds and chaines of a <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> and Antichriſtian captivity, from the remainder whereof (ſtill ſurviving) we hope and pray for a full deliverance by you. And for me, if my late <hi>teſtimony</hi> againſt the<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 11.7.</note> Beaſt may come in for a ſhare with thoſe<note n="b" place="margin">Ibid. v. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>two witneſſes</hi> mentioned in this <hi>ſixt Trumpet</hi> (which I am farre from arrogating to my ſelfe) then this I dare be bold to ſay, that your unanimous vote which called mee from Exile, is that <hi>Great voice from Heaven,</hi> ſaying to the Witneſſes, <hi>Come up hither.</hi> And was not that a <hi>Great voice,</hi> which was made up of the whole Houſe, none contradicting, when the widows petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for her exiled Husbands liberty was read and granted? And the Order for his liberty came it not to his Priſon juſt in the beginning of that moneth, which made up three yeeres and half, anſwering to three days &amp; a half, as here yee ſhall find it calculated? But I ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit all to the charitable &amp; judicious interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of your excellent wiſdomes. But little
<pb facs="tcp:157070:4"/> thoughts had I of ſuch a Parliament as this, when theſe <hi>Meditations</hi> were a working. And this I humbly pray you to take notice of, that I have, without any alteration, or addition, of ſecond thoughts, preſented theſe my <hi>Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> unto your Honours, as they were firſt conceived, that wherein (at ſuch a diſtance, as I then was) they have come home to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie, God may have the Glory, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhort, or wide, humane frailty may obtaine pitie and pardon. Now the Lord Ieſus Chriſt be pleaſed to continue his March before you, and fill your hearts more and more with all holy Zeale and invincible courage, to fight his ſpirituall Battell againſt the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and his Crew, that you being his <hi>Called,</hi> and <hi>Choſen,</hi> and <hi>Faithfull,</hi> may with the Lamb overcome, and reigne with him for evermore, which is and ever ſhall be the fervent prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your ever vowed Servant,</hi> Henry Burton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:157070:4"/>
            <head>The ſounding of the two laſt Trumpets, The ſixth and ſeventh: from <hi>Revel.</hi> 9.13. to the end of the eleventh Chapter: very uſefull, and much to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in theſe laſt times.</head>
            <div n="1-50" type="pages">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the whole Booke of the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is a prophecie of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of Gods Church, and of the grand enemies therof, from <hi>Iohns</hi> time, till time ſhould bee no more: So the ſounding of the <hi>ſeven Trumpets</hi> is a ſpeciall <hi>prophecie</hi> of things to come to paſſe in the very laſt times, on which wee are now falne, and more eſpecially the <hi>ſixt Trumpet</hi> points to theſe very preſent times, and the <hi>ſeventh</hi> to the now approching time, in the end whereof time ſhall have an end, and ſo bee ſwallowed up of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. And for the greater both obſervation and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:157070:5"/> confirmation of this laſt prophecie uttered by the Seven Trumpets, it is tribled in this book: firſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Seven Seals,</hi> Chap. 5.5. Secondly, here un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Seven Trumpets,</hi> Chap. 8.7, 8. And thirdly, under the <hi>Seven Vials,</hi> Chap. 15.16. The <hi>Seals</hi> are <hi>opened,</hi> that all may<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 6.1.3.5. &amp;c.</note> ſee: the <hi>Trumpets</hi> are <hi>ſounded,</hi> that all may heare: and the <hi>vials</hi> are <hi>powred out</hi> to the deſtruction of the enemies of Chriſt, and to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation of his Church. The whole Prophecie is ſet out in great State and magnificence: as by Chriſt the Lambe, and Lion of the Tribe of <hi>Juda,</hi> and from him by his holy Angels. All which ſhould draw our attention, as to matters and myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of higheſt excellencie. And we may note how theſe three Sevens doe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (as<note n="a" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Mede.</hi>
                  </note> ſome have well obſerved) that is, are coincident, and all fall within the ſame time, or like the wheels in<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezech.</hi> 1.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel,</hi> have their motion one within another. As (Chap. 8.1.) no ſooner is the <hi>ſeventh Seale</hi> opened, whereupon follows <hi>ſilence in heaven for halfe an houre:</hi> but <hi>John</hi> ſees the <hi>Seven Angels ſtanding before God,</hi> to whom were given the <hi>Seven Trumpets,</hi> Verſe 2. So as the iſſue of the <hi>Seven Seals</hi> falls upon the <hi>Seven Trumpets,</hi> as having their accompliſhment in them. But before they ſound, <hi>Another Angell ſtands at the Altar,</hi> the <hi>golden Altar before the throne,</hi> which is Chriſt, offering up <hi>much incenſe, with the prayers of all Saints,</hi> here below, which prayers, as incenſe, are accepted of God, Verſe 4. and out of the ſame <hi>Cenſer</hi> filled with fire <hi>from the Altar,</hi> the <hi>fire is caſt upon the Earth,</hi> whereupon the <hi>ſeven Angels with their ſeven Trumpets prepared to ſound.</hi> And who ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth their ſeven ſeverall Soundings, and the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:157070:5"/> effects thereof, with the ſeverall pourings forth of the <hi>ſeven Vials,</hi> and the effects thereof, hee ſhall obſerve ſuch a ſimilitude between them, as will put him out of all doubt, that the <hi>ſeven Trumpets</hi> and the <hi>ſeven Vials,</hi> are all one and the ſame <hi>Prophecie.</hi> Take a brief view hereof. The<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 8 7. <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.2.</note> ſounding of the <hi>firſt Trumpet,</hi> and the pouring forth of the firſt <hi>Viall</hi> ſmites the Earth: the<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.8. <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.3.</note> 
                  <hi>ſecond Trumpet</hi> and <hi>Viall,</hi> the Sea: the <hi>third Trumpet and Viall,</hi> the Rivers: the <hi>fourth Trumpet</hi> and <hi>Viall,</hi> the Sun: the <hi>fifth Trumpet</hi> and <hi>Viall,</hi> the Kingdome of the Beaſt, the throne whereof is chiefly in <hi>Rome;</hi> ſo as under this <hi>Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet</hi> and <hi>Viall,</hi> the <hi>Beaſts Kingdome</hi> is exceedingly<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.10. <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.1, 2, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>darkned,</hi> as <hi>with ſmoke out of the bottomleſſe pit,</hi> and the limbes of the Beaſt, the vaſſ is of his Kingdom of darkneſſe, even all ſuch, <hi>as have</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap</hi> 9 4. <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.3.</note> 
                  <hi>not the Seale of God in their fore-heads,</hi> are tormented by ſundry plagues, as Chap. 9. and 16.10, 11. So as this <hi>fifth Trumpet</hi> and <hi>Viall</hi> ſeems to ſet forth (not excluding the former; for they have all a concurrence in ſome degree one with another from the very firſt to the laſt) more cleerly the State of the Kingdome of the Beaſt, upon, and ſince the <hi>Councell of Trent,</hi> whereby through <hi>ſmokes out of the bottomleſſe pit,</hi> his whole Kingdome and Throne grew more darke, then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly they had been; of that ſmoke, never ſuch <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts</hi> bred, which for multitude, greatnes, and power, far exceed thoſe of <hi>Egypt,</hi> full of Martiall terrour (as Chap. 9.7, 8, 9, 10, 11.) whoſe <hi>King over them is the Angell of the bottomleſſe pit, Abaddon</hi> or <hi>Apollyon,</hi> a moſt cruell and mercileſſe deſtroyer. And that this is that Great Beaſt of <hi>Rome,</hi> with all his crew of Jeſuits and Friers, no queſtion is to be made. And
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:157070:6"/> here by the way, wee may cleerly ſee, that by the darkning of the <hi>throne of the Beaſt</hi> upon the powring out of the <hi>fifth Viall,</hi> is not to be underſtood the deſtruction of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe (as ſome have ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined) but thereby is meant that univerſall darknes ariſing from the <hi>ſmoke out of the bottomleſſe pit,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Kingdome of the Beaſt is altogether cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, like that palpable <hi>Egyptian</hi> darkneſſe, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate fere-running plague of the deſtruction of their <hi>Firſt-borne,</hi> and ſo of Iſraels finall and full deliverance, in the deſtruction of the whole power, and flower of <hi>Egypt.</hi> That this is ſo, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare but the <hi>fifth Viall,</hi> with the <hi>fifth Trumpet:</hi> in nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of which you ſhall find any touch or footſtep of <hi>Romes</hi> Ruine, but in both a wonderfull <hi>darkneſſe</hi> over that whole <hi>Throne and Kingdome,</hi> ſo as unto them (by reaſon of the ſmoke out of the pit, namely groſſe, palpable, and damnable colours and preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as a blacke veile to cover their Myſtery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, moſt cunningly woven up in the <hi>Councell of Trent,</hi> but firſt contrived in the Popes Conclave, the Beaſts Den, at <hi>Rome) the Sun and aire are altogether darkned,</hi> as with the black <hi>cloud</hi> towards the <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> while the bright <hi>pillar</hi> of the Goſpell ſhines forth cleerly to Gods people. And that this is the ſenſe aforeſaid, is manifeſt, not only by comparing the <hi>fifth Viall,</hi> with the <hi>fifth Trumpet,</hi> but alſo by conſidering, and comparing the <hi>ſixth Viall,</hi> with the <hi>ſixth Trumpet.</hi> For if it ſhall appeare, that we are now come within the Sound of the <hi>ſixth Trumpet,</hi> and under the time of the powring out of the <hi>ſixth Viall:</hi> then certainly the <hi>fifth Vial,</hi> and the <hi>fifth Trumpet</hi> are alreadie paſt (ſaving only that all the <hi>Vials</hi> are ſtill
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:157070:6"/> powring out, and all the <hi>Trumpets</hi> ſtill a ſounding, til they all conclude in and with the laſt). And if (for the mayn) paſt, and yet <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>ſeat of the Beaſt,</hi> unruined, then certainly by the darkning of the Seat of the Beaſt in the <hi>fifth Viall,</hi> cannot be meant the deſtruction of the <hi>Citie of Rome.</hi> And thus having by way of preface premiſed theſe things, which alſo may ſerve as a key to introduce us now to take a view of our propoſed matter, namely the <hi>ſixth Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet:</hi> wee now come, by the ſame Grace of God, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and guiding us, to ſuch Obſervations, as the Text all along preſents unto us, and wherin our eyes are infallible witneſſes of thoſe things which our eares doe heare from the ſound of this <hi>Trumpet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chap. 9.13. <hi>And the ſixt Angell ſounded, and I heard a voice from the foure hornes of the golden Altar, which is before God, ſaying to the ſixt Angell, which had the Trumpet, looſe the foure Angels, which are bound in the great River</hi> Euphrates: <hi>And the foure Angels were looſed, which were prepared for an houre, and a day, and a moneth, and a year, for to ſlay the third part of men, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the former verſe, after the ſounding of the fifth Angell, it is ſaid, <hi>One woe is paſt, and behold there comes two woes more hereafter.</hi> Whereupon it is added, <hi>And the ſixth Angell ſounded, &amp;c.</hi> This ſhews us by the way, that the ſounding of theſe ſeven Angels brings with it ſo many woes; even as the ſeven Vialls are called the ſeven laſt plagues. And theſe woes are denounced and doe fall upon the Beaſt and his crew: as thoſe ſeven laſt plagues al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo do; as yee may ſee, Chap. 9.4.20. Chap. 16.5.6.10. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Now by the <hi>voice from the foure hornes of the golden
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:157070:7"/> Altar,</hi> which is before God, is cleerely meant Chriſts own voice, who is that <hi>golden Altar,</hi> even that only true <hi>Altar,</hi> whereof that Levitical four-horned <hi>golden Altar</hi> was a type, and to which the Scripture here alludeth. For as on that Leviticall <hi>Altar</hi> all Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices and offerings were preſented unto God, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe they were not accepted: So Chriſt is our only<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.10.15. <hi>&amp;</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Altar,</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5.</note> in whoſe Name we offer up all our <hi>Spirituall Sacrifices acceptable to God by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And as offendors under the law fled for refuge to the hornes of the Altar: So we being offendors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, by our ſins, do fly for<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 6 18. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.1.2.</note> refuge to Chriſt, ſo as the purſuer, man, or devill, may<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33, 34</note> not meddle with us.</p>
               <p>Againe, Chriſts voice here ſhewes unto us that he is the great King, and Lord, that commands all things in heaven and earth, he it is, that ſendeth woes and plagues upon the enemies of his Church. He commandeth his Angels, and they execute his commands.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Looſe the foure Angells</hi> (ſaith hee, to his Angell) <hi>which are bound in the great river Euphrates.</hi> Before we can come to know whats meant by theſe four <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells,</hi> it behoves us firſt to enquire whats meant by the <hi>great river Euphrates.</hi> Of this <hi>great river Euphrates</hi> mention is made alſo in the<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.11.</note> 
                  <hi>ſixth viall,</hi> anſwering to this <hi>ſixt Trumpet.</hi> Now this <hi>great river Euphrates</hi> is that,<note place="margin">Herodotus.</note> which invironing <hi>Babylon,</hi> made it invincible, untill <hi>Cyrus,</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> did by his million of men cauſe the waters thereof neere about <hi>Babylon</hi> ſo to be drayned, into many deepe and vaſt ſluces or by-channels, as the maine river for a time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming fordable, his men waded through it, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:157070:7"/> ſo <hi>Babylon</hi> was ſurpriſed. And to this alludeth that which is written<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.12.</note> in the <hi>ſixt Viall,</hi> of the drying up of that great river, that the way of the Kings of the Eaſt might be prepared. Now the Kingdome of the beaſt, or his throne, againſt which the woes of the ſeven trumpets are ſounded, and the laſt plagues of the ſeven vialls powred out, is that <hi>Great</hi> Babylon, <hi>the mother of whordoms and abominations,</hi> and the great captiver of Gods people, as ſhe is at large, and cleerely ſet forth, Chap. 17. and. 18. And the <hi>Great river Euphrates,</hi> is that main ſtrength and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of men, whereby <hi>Babylon</hi> is defended againſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion. This main ſtrength of this <hi>Babylon</hi> is at this day the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> or the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Emperour in <hi>Germanie,</hi> and the reſt of that houſe, yea &amp; all thoſe of that faction and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacie, as the Hierarchie, or Prelacie, where ever it is, together with the wicked of the World that are made drunk with the Whores golden cup. It follows then, that thoſe <hi>foure Angells bound in the river Euphrates,</hi> whom Chriſt commands to be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, are thoſe chriſtian Kings, Princes, and States, which for a time, either ſtanding Neuters, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for <hi>Babylon,</hi> Chriſt raiſeth and rouſeth up to take up armes, for the diminiſhing and draining of this great River <hi>Euphrates</hi> by their numerous Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and potent preparations, v. 16. 17. &amp;c. Nor is it uncouth, to call Kings and Princes <hi>Angels;</hi> for they are often called<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal</hi> 82 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Elohim,</hi> Gods, as alſo the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly angells are. And Kings and Princes being<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Gods Miniſters,</hi> and being eſpecially ſent by him upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great buſineſſe, as here, they may therefore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be called <hi>Angells,</hi> which ſignifies, ſuch as are
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:157070:8"/> 
                  <hi>ſent.</hi> This is cleere enough. As Chap. 1.20. The Miniſters of the ſeven Churches are called <hi>Angels.</hi> And Chap. 12.17. <hi>Michael,</hi> and his Angels, do fight with the Dragon, and his Angels. And Chap. 17. Thoſe Kings which once warred for the Beaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt, even they ſhall one day <hi>hate the whore, and ſhall make her deſolate and naked.</hi> And the reaſon is there given (Verſe 17.) <hi>For God hath put in their hearts to fulfill his will, and to agree, and give their Kingdome unto the Beaſt, untill the words of God ſhall be fulfilled.</hi> And then he will call and ſend them, as his Angels or Meſſengers, to execute his will againſt the <hi>Whore.</hi> Even ſo here, the looſing of the <hi>foure Angels,</hi> which were <hi>bound in the great River Euphrates,</hi> is the raiſing up of certain Kings and Princes, which ſhall remove out of the way the maine ſtrength, whereby <hi>Babylon</hi> is guarded. And although this her ſtrength be very great, and as hard to remove out of the way, as to remove the <hi>Great River Euphrates</hi> out of her vaſt Chanell: yet theſe foure Angels thus looſed, ſhall ſo diminiſh <hi>Babylons</hi> ſtrong Fortreſſes, as a way ſhall be made for her ſurpriſall, and utter deſolation.</p>
               <p>This then being ſo cleere and plain, it points us as by the finger, to theſe very times, wherein God hath ſtirred up ſundry Kings and Princes, with their mighty armies to make war upon the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> the maine pillars of the Popedome. As the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> whoſe continued armie ſtill keepes the field againſt all the Emperours power, alſo the King of <hi>France,</hi> and the Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> with the States Generall (and I may ſay <hi>Generous</hi>) of the Low
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:157070:8"/> Countries. Theſe may wel be thoſe <hi>four Angels</hi> here looſed, which now make war againſt the ſtrength of <hi>Babylon.</hi> Theſe were <hi>readie at an houre,</hi> &amp;c. to obey Chriſts Command, and wil, (verſ. 15.) for to ſlay the third part of men. Look but upon the deſolations of <hi>Germany,</hi> &amp; look alſo upon the late admirable victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which the Lord of Hoſts, of Sea, &amp; Land, gave to the States General againſt the K. of <hi>Spains</hi> great Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy in the narrow Seas, wherein a third part at leaſt of the men periſhed; And the war is ſtill continued on all ſides againſt <hi>Babylons Euphrates,</hi> to abate the pride of her ſwelling ſtreams, wherwith <hi>Babylon</hi> is guarded.</p>
               <p>Again, the<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 16.</note> number of the Armies of theſe foure Angels, is ſaid to be, 200000 <hi>thouſand:</hi> ſuch an armie for number, as never was in the World. <hi>Cyrus</hi> (as is before noted) had 1000 thouſand to invade <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> which was the greateſt army that Hiſtory makes mention of. But loe here an armie, of 200 times ſo many, <hi>even</hi> 200000 <hi>thouſand,</hi> to make war againſt ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall <hi>Babylon,</hi> &amp; her temporal power. Now by this number ſo great, numbred by God himſelfe in this place, is eſpecially meant ſuch an armie, as ſhall be invincible againſt <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſuch an armie, I ſay, as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was in the world. For Gods numbring is his va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luing, or as he eſteems, &amp; accounts a thing. As when he was about to deſtroy that potent &amp; proud King of <hi>Babylon, Belſhazzar,</hi> then Emperour of the World, with his Princes and powers about him, he ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him,<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.26.</note> 
                  <hi>God hath numbred thy Kingdome,</hi> which is expounded by the next words, <hi>Thou art weighed in the ballance, and art found wanting.</hi> So as on the contrary, here, where God numbers ſuch an hoſt, as here, to be two hundred thouſand thouſand, the meaning is, that theſe foure Angells with their armie, ſhall bee
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:157070:9"/> ſo potent and formidable, and ſo victorious againſt <hi>Babylon,</hi> and all her forces, as if they conſiſted of ſuch a wonderfull number. For otherwiſe, God ſtands not upon numbers, it is<note n="q" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.6</note> 
                  <hi>all one with him to ſave by many or by few.</hi> And his few ſhall be, as many thouſand thouſands, when hee will get the victory by them. The King of <hi>Swedens</hi> army, which hee firſt brought into <hi>Germany,</hi> that got the victory o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Emperours mighty forces at <hi>Lipſich,</hi> was far ſhort in number of the Emperors thouſands.</p>
               <p>In the next place is deſcribed the manner of the horſemen, and of the horſes, verſ. 17. to ſet forth their power, and terrour: Then the manner of their fight: <hi>out of their mouthes iſsued fire, ſmoke, and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, wherewith the third part of men were killed.</hi> Here we ſee the manner of weapons and fight of theſe very times of ours, as by powder and ſhot, ſignified by fire, ſmoke, and brimſtone, comming out of their mouthes, as out of the mouth of the Cannon, thoſe murthering weapons. With theſe are ſlaine the third part of men. This, deſolate <hi>Germany</hi> can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, now turned almoſt into a Wilderneſſe. And in that the horſes are ſaid to hurt with their mouthes, and with their tayls: thereby is meant, that there is no ſecuritie from being hurt of them every way, both before and behind. And in that their tayls are ſaid to have heads like Serpents, it doth argue, that this army againſt <hi>Babylon</hi> is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly potent, but prudent and politicke in managing of the warre.</p>
               <p>And where it is ſaid, Verſe 20. That <hi>the reſt of the men, which were not killed by theſe plagues, yet repented not of the works of their hands, that they ſhould not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:157070:9"/> Devils, and Idols of gold, and ſilver, and braſse, and ſtone, and of wood,</hi> which neither <hi>can ſea, nor heare, nor walke: Neither repented they of their mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, nor of their ſorceries, nor of their fornication, nor of their thefts:</hi> hence we note, theſe particulars: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, that all this warre, all theſe plagues (as is touched before) are againſt ſpirituall <hi>Babylon,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Kingdome of the Beaſt, and the head and body of Popery. Secondly, (for confirmation here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> this Spirituall <hi>Babylon,</hi> notwithſtanding all her ſmooth evaſions, and ſhifts to put it off (as the<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.20.</note> whore in the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> wipes her lips and ſaith, <hi>I have done no wickedneſse</hi>) is found to be a notorious and egregious Idolatreſſe, in as much, as all her Images of gold, ſilver, braſſe, ſtone, wood, are here in plain termes called Idols, as which can neither ſee, nor heare, nor walke. Yet Papiſts doe give that worſhip and honour unto them, as if they did both ſee, and heare, and walke, yea, as if they had a very Deity in them. And this is that <hi>Spirituall</hi> fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that <hi>great Whore,</hi> (Chap. 17.3.) <hi>with whom the Kings of the earth have committed fornication, and the inhabitants of the earth have beene made drunke with the nine of her fornication;</hi> as being no leſſe mad upon her Images and Idols, and other ſervice deviſed by men, then Drunkards are upon new Wine. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is this <hi>Babylon the Great</hi> called <hi>the Mother of whordoms, and abominations of the earth,</hi> Ver. 5. But yet for al this you muſt not cal her ſo, She wil be called no other, but the <hi>Holy Catholike Church,</hi> the <hi>chaſt Spouſe of</hi> Chriſt. Thirdly, I note here, that all her idolatrous <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Service in her Image-worſhip is the worſhip of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils: &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequently all Papiſts are the Devils vaſſals
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:157070:10"/> and ſervants. A hard doome (you will ſay) but it is as true, as Gods Word here is true. Fourthly, Notwithſtanding all this, and that God plagues the Beaſt and his brood, and wars againſt <hi>Babylon,</hi> with his terrible armies, and doth and will prevaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her, yet ſhe is altogether incorrigible, incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, though they ſee the third part of them ſlain, yet the reſt will not repent of their Idolatry, and other <hi>Babylonian</hi> ſins, as murthering of Gods Saints and Martyrs, uſing Witchcraft and Sorcery, authorizing of publike Stews, and that for money, and robbing and cheating the ſimple people of their money by their Mountebanke Maſſes, Diſpenſations and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons, and a thouſand ſuch like trumpery, being thoſe ſins that are proper to <hi>Babylon,</hi> to this Kingdome of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> the Beaſt. Fiftly, I note, here, that God rayſeth armies againſt <hi>Babylon,</hi> &amp; cuts her ſhort, and powres many and grievous plagues upon her, thereby to bring her to repentance, or otherwiſe to leave her unexcuſable. And ſo much of the ninth Chapter.</p>
               <p>Now follows the tenth Chapter, wherein are ſome things obſervable, that fall under this <hi>Sixt Trumpet.</hi> And ſo what wee find written in this and the next Chapter, till we come to the Seventh, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs all to this <hi>Trumpet.</hi> This tenth Chapter is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry myſticall. For here are voices of ſeven thunders uttered, but ſealed up, and unwritten. Yet becauſe the very ſound of thunder leaves ſome impreſſion behind it, and though mans underſtanding cannot interpret it, yet the Conſcience, being ſtrucke with terrour, will pick ſome meaning out of it: therefore taking the Scripture ſtill for our guide, we will aſſay to ſpeak ſomething of this Chap. by the way. In the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:157070:10"/> firſt Verſe an Angel is ſent out with great Majeſty. This requires attention to what followeth: He hath a <hi>Little Book</hi> in his hand, Verſe 2.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 2, 3, 4.</note> Of which more is ſpoken from the eighth Verſe to the end of the Chapter. The next thing of marke is the ſeven Thunders uttering their voices, but ſealed up; and this followeth immediatly upon the Angels ſetting his right foot upon the Sea, and his left foot on the Earth, crying with a loud voice, as when a Lion roareth. This is very myſticall. But this Angell, by his deſcription, ſhould bee Chriſt: the ſame that is deſcribed, Chapter. 1.13, 14, 15, 16. His ſtanding with one foot on the Sea, and another on the Land, ſeemes to allude to<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.15.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſtanding on the Sea ſide, and ſtretching his Rod over the Sea, and crying with a ſtrong voice of Prayer to God. Or it alludeth to the<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 3.14, 15, 16.</note> dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the Prieſts feet in the brim of <hi>Iordan,</hi> ſo ſoon as the one foot touched the water, the Streame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coyled, and gave way. Both theſe were Types of Chriſt, and of his Church. And this which is here written, falling under this <hi>Sixt Trumpet,</hi> is a prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the deſtruction of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and of the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Gods people. Upon this cry follows the voice of the ſeven thunders, but ſealed up. The voice of Thunder is the<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 29.</note> voice of God. So the Heathen called their God<note n="x" place="margin">Iupiter Alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonans <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Hom.</note> 
                  <hi>Iupiter,</hi> the thundring God. But this voice uttered, is ſealed up. But theſe thunders will ſpeak plain enough in the next <hi>Trumpet,</hi> as alſo under the ſeventh <hi>Viall,</hi> when they ſhall take their effect in blaſting and conſuming the Kingdome of the Beaſt. For the voice of the Thunders is a Prophecie to be fulfilled in the Next Trumpet. As
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:157070:11"/> alſo (Verſe 5, 6, 7.) the Angell ſpeaketh what ſhall be under the voice of the Seventh Angell. And there is a ſecret meaning in the voice of the thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which is expreſſed, not in words, but in the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects. As the Lord ſaith,<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal</hi> 81.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou calledſt in trouble, and I delivered thee, I anſwered thee in the ſecret of thunder.</hi> This is ſpoken of <hi>Iſraels</hi> deliverance from <hi>Egypt,</hi> where they cried to the Lord; and he plagued the <hi>Egyptians</hi> by his thunder; and of their paſſage thorow the Sea, when <hi>Moſes</hi> cried to the Lord, and he anſwered his cry in giving paſſage for his people, and in the ſecret of his thunder in deſtroying the <hi>Egyptians.</hi> Even as <hi>David</hi> ſaith alſo in another Pſalme, where elegantly deſcribing that miraculous deliverance through the Sea: <hi>The waters ſaw thee, O God, the waters ſaw thee, they were afraid, the depths al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo were troubled, the clouds powred out water, the Skies ſent out a ſound, thine arrows alſo went abroad:</hi> he addeth <hi>The voice of thy thunder was in the Heaven, the Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings lightned the World, the earth trembled and ſhooke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is that <hi>thunder,</hi> in the ſecret whereof the Lord heard the cry of his people, in delivering them, and in diſcomfiting and deſtroying their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. And thus here, the voice of theſe <hi>ſeven thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> is ſealed up, and reſerved to be interpreted by the voice of the ſeventh Angell, when theſe thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſhall have their effect upon the Beaſt in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. For thus alſo that which followeth (as before is touched) of the Angels Swearing, that time ſhould be no more, is to be fulfilled under the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Trumpet, when alſo the Myſtery of God ſhall be finiſhed, when all Prophecies ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, and in the end of the World, all
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:157070:11"/> time ſhall be ſwallowed up of Eternity, as before. Which by the way noteth unto us, that the Seventh Trumpet ſhall continue ſounding, and the ſeventh Viall powring forth, untill the end of time.</p>
               <p>Shall time then have an end? certainly. Here then a queſtion may bee moved, what ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the Sun and Moone, and Starrs, whoſe motion is meaſured out by time, and which diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth the<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.14.</note> times and ſeaſons, days, months and yeeres of this inferiour world? For anſwere where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto in brief, becauſe the queſtion is full of curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, whether thoſe glorious creatures ſhall ceaſe to be, or their motion ſhall ceaſe, as whereof there ſeemes to be no more uſe, I find not clearly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed: but this I find; There ſhall be <hi>a new</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10, 12.</note> 
                  <hi>heaven, and a new earth,</hi> when the <hi>heavens being on fire ſhall bee diſſolved, and the elements ſhall melt with fervent heate, and the earth alſo, and the workes that are therein ſhall be burnt up.</hi> But how this ſhall be, or in what parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular State or forme, it is not revealed. Only this reſolution is the beſt, which <hi>Peter</hi> gives:<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Seeing</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>all theſe things ſhal be diſſolved, what manner of perſons ought yee to be in all holy converſation, and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse, looking for, and haſtning unto, the comming of the day of God,</hi> &amp;c.<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Nevertheleſse</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>we, according to his promiſe, looke for new heavens, and a new earth, wherein dwelleth righteouſneſse.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It followeth, Verſe 8, &amp;c. Here <hi>John</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to take the little Book, which was open in the Angels hand, who takes it, and eats it up, which becomes <hi>ſweet in his mouth,</hi> but <hi>bitter in his belly:</hi> and thereupon he is bid to prophecie before <hi>many people, and Nations, and Tongues, and Kings.</hi> And this is the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:157070:12"/> ſumme of the foure laſt Verſes of this Chapter. It is cleer, that this little Book ſignifieth, or containeth thoſe prophecies, which <hi>John,</hi> and in him Chriſts Miniſters under this Trumpet (called his witneſſes in the eleventh Chapter) were to publiſh to the World. For upon the receiving of the Book, hee is bid to prophecie. This place alludes to that in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechiel,</hi> Chap. 2.9, 10. and Chap. 3.1, 2, 3. where the Prophet beholds an <hi>hand</hi> ſent unto him, and a <hi>rowle of a book</hi> therein, which was ſpread before him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and without, and there was written therein <hi>Lamentations, and mourning, and wo:</hi> and hee was bid to eate this rowle, and to go and ſpeake unto the houſe of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> which hee eating, found it in his mouth ſweet as honey. A juſt parallell to this little booke here, all circumſtances compared toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. So as this little booke containeth for the matter of it, thoſe judgements of God, which <hi>Iohn</hi> was to denounce in his propheſying to fall upon the Beaſt, and his Kingdome. The ſweetneſſe of it in his mouth, argues the<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 39.8.</note> goodneſſe of Gods Word, even when it denounceth judgements for ſinne; whereupon if men bee brought to repent, it is ſweet as honey in the mouth: but if they heare, and doe not repent, it goes downe into the belly, and the effects thereof prove <hi>bitterneſse in the end.</hi> The Apoſtle ſaith that Gods Word is the<note n="c" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15.</note> 
                  <hi>ſweet ſavour of God in them that are ſaved, and in them that periſh.</hi> Againe, this ſweetneſſe in the mouth of <hi>John,</hi> and bitterneſſe in his belly, ſhewes, that Gods meſſage ſhould be ſweete to his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, in receiving it, and delivering it with their mouth, although in the iſſue it prove bitter unto
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:157070:12"/> them, as being the cauſe and occaſion of much trouble and perſecution, which they ſuffer of the World; ſuch as befell the Prophets and Apoſtles, and Miniſters of Chriſt in all ſucceding ages; and as we ſhall ſee more particularly in the next Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to which we now come.</p>
               <p>Chap. 11.1. &amp;c. <hi>And there was given me a reed like unto a rod, and the Angel ſtood, Saying, Riſe and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the Temple of God, and the Altar, and them that worſhip therein: But the Court which is without the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, leave out, and meaſure it not: for it is given unto the Gentiles, and the holy Citie ſhall they tread underfoot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and two moneths. And I will give power unto my two witneſses, and they ſhall propheſie a thowſand, two hundred, and threeſcore days, clothed in Sackcloth, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Still we are to rememb r (as before is noted) that wee are yet within the compaſſe of the ſixt Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet. So as what is here laid downe, untill we come to the Seventh Trumpet, Verſe 15. muſt bee inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted, as appertaining to the ſixt Trumpet. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Sixt Trumpet then all this is done. <hi>John</hi> here repreſents (as I ſaid thoſe faithfull Miniſters, or witneſſes of Chriſt, here mentioned, who living under this ſixt Trumpet, muſt riſe, and take the reed, and meaſure the Temple and the Altar, but muſt not meaſure the Court without the Temple, but leave it out. Firſt, they m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt riſe, that is, begin to beſtir themſelves in their Miniſtery. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in muſt they exerciſe themſelves? In meaſuring the Temple, and the Altar, with the reed in the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells hand. This alludes to that meaſuring <hi>Reede</hi> which <hi>Ezechiell</hi> ſaw in a viſion, wherewith he mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured the Temple &amp;c. as Chapter 40. and 41. &amp;c.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:157070:13"/> Now by the <hi>Temple</hi> here is meant the true Church of Chriſt, as is cleer by many places, as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16.17. 2. Cor. 6.16. Eph. 2.21. And in many places of this booke of the Revelation, Temple is taken for the Church of Chriſt: as Chap. 15.5.6. and in the 19 verſe of this Chapter, and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where. And by the reede in the Angells hand to meaſure withall, is meant the ſtraight rule of Gods word, by which alone the true Church of Chriſt being meaſured, is thereby known and diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from all falſe and pretended Churches. And that <hi>John,</hi> Chriſts Miniſter is bid to riſe, and thus to meaſure Gods Temple, his Church, doth plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly argue, that in the time of this Trumpet the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Antichriſt ſhall ariſe, and make a loud claim to the title of the Temple, as pertaining pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly to them, and to none other. Among many other, take one famous inſtance. What a notorious booke is publiſhed of late by the Prelate of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury?</hi> wherein he ſweats and labours to prove, that the only true Catholike Church of Chriſt over the world is made up of the many Prelaticall Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, as the proper members of the body; ſo as he makes the Church of <hi>England</hi> and of <hi>Rome</hi> to be all one Church; and finally ſhuts out all reformed Proteſtant Churches, that have no Prelates, as no true Churches of Chriſt. And becauſe his ſingle word (which is his beſt and only argument) may the better paſſe without controule, hee goes about tooth and naile to cry downe the ſufficiencie of the Scriptures, as being an imperfect rule of it ſelfe to meaſure the Church by. And this his Booke he hath beene ſo bold, as to dedicate to the King,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:157070:13"/> and makes it the faith of his Church of <hi>England,</hi> as profeſſing one Faith and Religion with <hi>Rome.</hi> Is it not high time then for ſome <hi>John,</hi> or other faithful Miniſters of Chriſt, to riſe, and take the meaſuring Reed in his hand, Gods Word, and therewith ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly meaſure the Temple of God, Chriſts Church, that it may be diſtinguiſhed and differenced from all falſe pretended Churches, and in eſpeciall from the Antichriſtian Hierarchie, the prelaticall Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church (as the<note n="d" place="margin">In his laſt reprinted Conference Epiſt. Dedic. p. 16. and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where in his Book.</note> Prelate cals his Church) in which Catholike, his <hi>Church of</hi> England, <hi>and of</hi> Rome <hi>are both one and the ſame</hi> Church; <hi>No doubt of that?</hi> They be the Prelats owne words. So as when the Prelate was ſo Zealous to bring <hi>Scotland</hi> to a conformitie with <hi>England,</hi> and when the <hi>Scots</hi> read in his Book <hi>Englands</hi> conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie with <hi>Rome,</hi> as to be one Church, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe one Faith and Religion with <hi>Rome:</hi> might not this (trow you) ſtartle and move the <hi>Scots</hi> to expell and repell, to thruſt out and keepe out at the Speares point this Conformity? And ſo might not the Prelates falſe Hierarchicall Catholike Church, (excluding all Proteſtant Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches from being any true Churches of Chriſt) juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly incenſe the Zealous hearts of <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſeeing Chriſt thus to be diſhonoured, and thruſt out of his Throne, and Antichriſts Prelates to be ſo mounted aloft, to caſt out ſuch uſurping Lords, that ſo none but Chriſt, according to his Word, and the Lords Anointed, according to his juſt Laws, might rule over them? Thus we ſee how neceſſary this mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring of the Temple is under this ſixt Trumpet, and what a cleere note it is of the time, wherein this ſixt Trumpet is ſounded. So as we may boldly ſay,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:157070:14"/> upon ſuch cleere evidence, that now is the time of the ſixt Trumpet, when there is ſuch need of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring the <hi>Temple</hi> with the <hi>Reed,</hi> thereby to know and vindicate, and ſeparate Chriſts true Church, from all counterfeit and Antichriſtian Churches, that at this time doe ſo boaſt themſelves for the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true Catholike Church of Chriſt. As (in <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi>) the uncertaine Authour upon <hi>Matthew,</hi> Chap. 24. hath obſerved. <hi>Let them which are in Iudea, flee to the Mountains:</hi> that is, ſaith hee, let all true <hi>Chriſtians flie to the Scriptures:</hi> for in the time of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, it will bee impoſsible to know the true Church from the falſe, but only by the Scriptures. So hee. But the ſaid Prelate of <hi>Canterburie</hi> rejects the Scripture from being a ſufficient and perfect meaſuring <hi>Reed</hi> of the Temple: and good reaſon, becauſe on the one ſide, the Prelate makes the Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchie to be of the very eſſence of the Catholike Church: and on the other ſide, the Scripture no where approveth of Prelacie, or of Dioceſan Lord Biſhops, it knows none ſuch: yea, and both<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 20. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 3 <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.10.</note> Chriſt forbade it to his Apoſtles, and they after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards never practiſed it themſelves, but expreſly condemned it in all; as in the Reply to the Prelates Relation, the Author hath cleerly proved.</p>
               <p>Come wee now to the meaſuring of the <hi>Altar.</hi> As the Temple, and Tabernacle under the Law, had their juſt meaſures and Dimenſions preſcribed of God: ſo alſo the Leviticall <hi>Altar.</hi> Now under the Law there was but one <hi>Altar,</hi> one for burnt offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, and one for incenſe: both theſe, as one, were types and figures of Chriſt, the true and only <hi>Altar</hi> under the <hi>Goſpell.</hi> For as the Altar under the Law did Sanctifie every guift and offering upon it (as
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:157070:14"/> 
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 29.37. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.19.) ſo Chriſt is to us that only <hi>Altar,</hi> on which wee offering our ſelves and our Spiritual Sacrifices, both are Sanctified and accepted of God. This is that <hi>Altar (Heb.</hi> 13.10.) of which the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>We have an Altar, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they have no right to eate, which ſerve the Tabernacle.</hi> That this Altar is Chriſt, and only Chriſt, is cleer, becauſe He being come, who is the true Altar, the typicall altar muſt altogether ceaſe. Otherwiſe thoſe who ſtill ſerved the Tabernacle, might have had right to eate of our Altar, could the Type and the Truth have conſiſted together. And the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle expreſly applyes this Altar, which wee Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians have, to Chriſt, as Verſe 11, 12, 13, 15. where he ſhowes the proper uſe of this Altar in ſanctifying our offerings, concluding and ſaying, <hi>By him therefore let us offer the Sacrifice of praiſe to God, continually, that is, the fruit of our lips, giving thanks to his name. By him,</hi> that is, by Chriſt, our <hi>Altar, in his Name,</hi> we muſt offer up all our <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> that ſo they may be Sanctified, and accepted of God. This is ſo cleere, that no ſober Divine, that underſtands any thing at all, can deny. So as the meaſuring of the Altar here, is (as the meaſuring of the Temple, whereof wee have ſpoken before) the vindicating of Chriſt to be the true and only Altar of true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. And this is a dutie enjoyned all faithfull Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and eſpecially under this Sixt Trumpet, in theſe our very times, wherein we have ſeen ſuch fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Romiſh Zeale in hoyſing up of Altars every where, and boldly maintaining both in<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> Pock <hi>in his</hi> Altare l. Chriſtianum. <hi>Rather</hi> Dam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenum.</note> Books and Sermons, the neceſſary uſe of ſuch their deviſed Altars of wood and ſtone, as without which God
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:157070:15"/> cannot be ſerved, nor their Sacrifices ſanctified: wheras theſe their Altars, with al their Altar-ſervice &amp; worſhip of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s deviſing, are not only derogatory from Chriſt the only true Altar, but alſo a flat de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall of Chriſt, and a very Maſſe of all Heatheniſh impietie, and atheiſticall infidelitie, and Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian apoſtacie. For that multitude of wooden and ſtone altars, which our Prelates do erect in all their Churches, are taken rather from the Heathen, as King<note n="g" place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Ahaz</hi> and his Prieſt framed their Altar according to the pattern of that at <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> or from <hi>Rome,</hi> which took them from the Heathen, or from the <hi>Iews,</hi> but if they ſay they take them from the <hi>Jewes,</hi> (as they doe many other of their Rites) then they very much forget them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and that in two mayne points: firſt, becauſe the Church of the <hi>Iewes</hi> had but<note n="h" place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 32.12</note> one altar for Incenſe, and Sacrifice, and that was at <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> they might not ſet up Altars in any other place, ſo as in their ſeventy yeeres captivitie in <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> they had no altar there: and at this day, the Temple and Altar at <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> being demoliſhed, they have no Altar, as no Sacrifice, or Incenſe. So as no <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and no Temple there, no Altar now of wood, or ſtone, or any other matter or mettle is to be ſet up in the worſhip of God. But the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> with all their Prelats, and Prieſts, doe ſet up in their Temples, not only one, but infinite numbers of Altars; according to that which the Prophet ſaith, of revolted <hi>Iſraell,</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Becauſe</hi> Iſraell <hi>hath made many Altars to ſin, Altars ſhall be unto him to ſin.</hi> And <hi>According to the multitude of his fruit, he hath increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Altars.</hi> And if they object, and ſay, <hi>Iſraell</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:157070:15"/> built Altars to other Gods: I anſwere, ſo they did, &amp; to the true God too, as they prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, as at <hi>Bethel</hi> and <hi>Dan.</hi> But all theſe their Altars were alike abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable to God, and for which he utterly caſt them out. And indeed all falſe Altars, with their ſervice (what ever men pretend to the contrary) are ſet up, and done to the<note n="k" place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11.15.</note> Devill, who in <hi>Ierobohams</hi> calves, and on thoſe Altars was worſhiped. And ſuch Altars, ſuch ſervice as men have deviſed, are not done to God, he utterly abhors them. Such are all Popiſh Altars, and Altar-Service.</p>
               <p>Secondly, as theſe Altar-worſhipers tranſgreſſe in the multitude of their Altars: ſo alſo in the meaſure of them, they doe not obſerve that due proportion preſcribed in Gods Law, but ſome are bigger, ſome leſſer, ſome longer, ſome ſhorter, ſome higher, ſome lower, as pleaſeth mans fancie. And therefore theſe their Altars are in no reſpect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to Gods law, but they are meere heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Damaſcen Altars, either of mans, or of the Devills deviſing, chuſe which they will.</p>
               <p>Now ſuch Altars, with all their pompous ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, being in theſe our dayes, ſo outragiouſly cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up in all prelaticall Churches, not only in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, but deſperate defiance of Chriſt, the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true Altar of all true Chriſtians: and whereas under this Sixt Trumpet Chriſt gives ſuch a charge to his ſervant <hi>John,</hi> and ſo to all his faithfull Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpell, to take the Reed that is in his hand, his holy word, and therewith to take a juſt meaſure, as of the Temple, his Church, that all may know and diſtinguiſh it from Antichriſts falſe Church; ſo of the Altar, which is himſelfe,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:157070:16"/> that all may know wee Chriſtians have no other Altar, whereon to offer our Spirituall Sacrifices acceptable to God, but only Chriſt, all other altars, being falſe and counterfeit, heatheniſh and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous, and a ſervice done to the Devill, and not to God, as being altogether and directly contrary to his Word, and a flat deniall of Chriſt the true and only Altar: hence we may ſafely conclude, that this is the very time of the ſixt Trumpet, wherein wee now live. How ought the true Miniſters of Chriſt then in theſe our dayes to beſtir themſelves, and fall a meaſuring the true Temple and Altar, and that with no other Reed, but that in Chriſts hand, and with no other Rule, but his owne word, that ſo his people (being truly and thorowly informed which is the true Church of Chriſt, and which the falſe and Antichriſtian Church, which the Prelats place in their Hierarchie; and which is the true and only Altar, whereon to offer all their Sacrifices, that they may be ſanctified and accepted of God, namely Jeſus Chriſt, and that therefore all other Altars, and Altar-Service deviſed by man, are abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable in Gods ſight) may have no more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with ſuch Altars, and ſuch Altar-Service, then with Antichriſt, whoſe Altars and Service they be? Otherwiſe, ſuch as communicate with them cannot be called the people of God, but are indeed the members of Antichriſt. For, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith,<note n="l" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor</hi> 6 14, 15, 16.</note> 
                  <hi>What fellowſhip hath righteouſneſſe with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe? And what communion hath light with darkneſſe? And what concord hath Chriſt with</hi> Belial? <hi>Or what part hath hee that believeth with an infidell? And what agreement hath the Temple of God with I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols?
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:157070:16"/> For yee are the Temple of the living God, as God hath ſaid, I will dwell in them, and walk in them, and I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo we come to the third thing here to be meaſured, and that is, Them that worſhip there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; that is, thoſe that are true members of Chriſts true Church, that are<note n="m" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.21, 22.</note> 
                  <hi>living ſtones</hi> of that living Temple, that are the<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.23, 24.</note> 
                  <hi>true worſhipers,</hi> which wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God in Spirit and Truth, that worſhip at no other Altar, but Jeſus Chriſt, praying and praiſing God in his name. Theſe be they, here, whom, with the Temple, and the Altar, <hi>John,</hi> and the Miniſters of Chriſt, and more eſpecially under this Sixt Trumpet, are to meaſure with the ſame Reede, So as the true people of God may be known and diſtinguiſhed from thoſe that be falſe and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit profeſſors, falſe and counterfeit Chriſtians. For under this Trumpet, how many thouſands (I ſpeak not of thoſe in the profeſt Popiſh Churches, but) even in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> where the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel hath been a long time imbraced, preached, and profeſſed, do<note n="o" place="margin">Though now ſince this Treatiſe was written, we ſee (bleſſed be God) by a late Order from the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted.</note> communicate with Altars, and with the Superſtitious and Idolatrous worſhip and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice thereunto appertaining according to humane Ordinances and Inventions: and yet would paſſe in the ranke of good Chriſtians and Proteſtants, who if they knew what it were to worſhip at Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, they would abhorre all ſuch Service? How ought Miniſters therefore in theſe times to take the juſt meaſure of thoſe that be true Chriſtians, by teaching the people out of Gods Word what a true Chriſtian is, and wherein hee muſt differ from all ſuch falſe Chriſtians, as communicate with Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:157070:17"/> in altar-Service and Worſhip, which is ſo rife, and ruffleth ſo pompouſly in this our time, whereby it appeareth plainly, that now the ſixt Trumpet is a ſounding? But perhaps Miniſters will plead for themſelves, that if they ſhall ſo doe, they muſt neceſſarily undergoe great perſecutions, and ſuffer at leaſt the loſſe of their Livings, and perhaps of their liberty too, and of their bloud, and members of their bodie, and of all they have, as ſome others have lately done. If this they ſtand upon, and ſo for feare forbeare to doe their dutie: they may then ſit them downe, confeſsing they are no faithfull Miniſters of Chriſt, as <hi>Iohn</hi> here was for obeying the command of Jeſus Chriſt. Much leſſe will ſuch ever prove ſuch witneſſes, as by and by are mentioned in this Chapter, who, forbearing teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to the truth, are willing to lay downe their precious lives. But of this in its proper place.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe</hi> 2.</note>It followeth: <hi>But the Court, which is without the Temple, leave out, and meaſure it not: for it is given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>and the holy Citie ſhall they tread under foot forty and two moneths.</hi> This Court without the Temple alludes to that utmoſt large court, which was without the Temple in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where all the common <hi>Jews</hi> aſſembled, as alſo thoſe of other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And this court without the Temple here, by a Metonymie, taking the continent for the thing contained, may ſignifie the company of thoſe in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, that profeſſe to be Chriſtians, but yet are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed and in truth no true members of the true Church, they are not of and in the Temple, but they are out of the Temple. And therefore that which is tranſlated in our Engliſh, <hi>Leave out,</hi> is in the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:157070:17"/> Originall <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Caſt out,</hi> as alſo the<note n="p" place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>jce forat.</note> Latine, and the<note n="*" place="margin">jette hors.</note> French rightly render it. This is, as the Lord ſaith to <hi>Ieremie,</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 15.19.</note> 
                  <hi>If thou take forth the precious from the vile, thou ſhalt be as my mouth.</hi> So here, <hi>Iohn</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving meaſured the true people of God, ſuch as wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him according to his Word: is bid here to caſt out the refuſe, ſuch as do not worſhip God in purity and verity, ſuch as worſhip not in his Temple, and at his Altar, to wit, in Chriſts only Name; who though they beare the common name of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, yet they are not within the Temple, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, in the common-outer court, which here is caſt out, and not to be reckoned to bee of the Temple. And this court <hi>Iohn</hi> muſt not meaſure: it ſufficeth, that having meaſured the true worſhippers, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing their true properties out of Gods Word: it followeth conſequently, that all thoſe, which are falſ worſhippers, are thoſe of the court without the Temple, &amp; ſo to be caſt out, (as<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.30.</note> the bond woman and her ſonne were caſt out of <hi>Abrahams</hi> houſe) and not to be meaſured, nor nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred with Gods people.</p>
               <p>And it is added here, <hi>For it is given unto the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles:</hi> that is, they of this court are to be reckoned among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and to bee accounted as Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and Infidels. For the purpoſe: what are all Papiſts, and all other altar-worſhippers, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in, and ſetters up, and Conformiſts to ſtrange Service invented by men, but Heathen and Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels? For as we ſaid before, the very ſetting up of an Altar, and Altar-Service, is a flat deniall of Chriſt the only true Altar, and ſo is meere Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſme and Infidelitie. Or elſe by the <hi>Gentiles</hi> here is underſtood the antichriſtian Kingdome, or
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:157070:18"/> the ſpirituall <hi>Babylon,</hi> under which the formall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants and cold profeſſours of this age, under the ſixt Trumpet, ſhall be brought in bondage, as back-ſliding <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old was given into the hands of the King of <hi>Babylon.</hi> For theſe back-ſliders and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliſts, are thoſe of the outer court, that is caſt out, and the Spirituall <hi>Babylon</hi> is properly ſo called, for her Heatheniſh and <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> manners, (as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 59.5.8. <hi>David</hi> calls <hi>Saul</hi> and his bloudy perſecutors, Heathen: and <hi>Eſay</hi> 1.10. the Prophet calls the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate Princes and people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Princes of <hi>Sodome,</hi> and people of <hi>Gomorrha,</hi> as being in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners like unto them) eſpecially her manifold Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, wherein ſhe reſembleth old <hi>Babylon,</hi> as ſhee is ſet out, Chap. 17. And how truly is this verified of our cold, or rather luke-warme <hi>Laodiceans</hi> in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> at this day? Is not all <hi>England</hi> in generall, and for the greateſt part, brought under the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> yoke in her univerſall conformitie to Popery in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up of Altars and Altar-ſervice, after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>Rome?</hi> Are not all the Miniſters and People therein (I ſay for the moſt part) made the Prelates vaſſals, who have of late, more then formerly, ſet up the Image of the Beaſt, and his Throne, almoſt in all the Churches, and over all the Congregations of <hi>England?</hi> What Miniſter almoſt is there at this day, dare ſtand againſt the Antichriſtian Tyranny, now ſo highly exalted over all mens conſciences? Are they not then brought under the Babyloniſh Captivitie? Are they not given to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> into the power of the Spirituall <hi>Babylon,</hi> a farre worſe and more intolerable bondage, then that of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient people of God, either in <hi>Egypt,</hi> or <hi>Babylon?</hi> For
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:157070:18"/> that was a bondage of the body: but this of the Soule and Conſcience. And thus this very phraſe, <hi>[It is given to the Gentiles]</hi> alludes to the like ſpeeches in the Prophets, concerning revolted and degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> whereof it is ſaid very frequently in<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 32.24, 25 28.</note> 
                  <hi>Jeremy,</hi> that the Citie is given into the hands of the <hi>Caldaeans,</hi> or <hi>Babylonians.</hi> So here the Court without the Temple is caſt out, and given to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> that is (as is ſaid before) to the Kingdome and power of the <hi>Babylonian</hi> Beaſt, which ſucceeds old <hi>Babylon</hi> in all her Idolatries, and beſtiall cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, in captiving of Gods people.</p>
               <p>And it is added here, <hi>And the holie Citie ſhall they tread under foot two and forty months.</hi> This holy Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty here alludes to the old City <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> as the <hi>Gentiles</hi> here allude to old <hi>Babylon,</hi> which did tread under feete that holy City 70. yeeres. But what is meant here by this holy City? This holy City is the true church of God, called the<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46.4.</note> city of God, and the<note n="u" place="margin">1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 11.32.</note> elect City, and the<note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.9.</note> beloved city, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine (<hi>Revell.</hi> 22.19.) the holy city, and the<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22.</note> City of the living God, the heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> This ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly City, this Church of God ſhal the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> to wit, the Spirituall <hi>Babylon,</hi> (called the Beaſt out of the bottomleſſe pit, Verſe 7.) <hi>tread under foote,</hi> that is, ſhall exceedingly oppreſſe and afflict, making ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vock of the Saints of God, the citizens of this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly city, making no more account of them, then of dirt and mire in the Streets; yea they ſhall defile and deſtroy the holy aſſemblies of the Saints, by corrupting the pure worſhip and ſervice of God, and crying downe all holineſſe, both of life and converſation, and Sanctification of the Sabbath or
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:157070:19"/> Lords day, in the publike aſſemblies, and private families, forbidding preaching of the doctrine of Grace, and reſtraining Sermons on the Lords day in the Afternoone, and perſecuting all Godly, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull, and painfull Miniſters, and giving publike diſpenſation to youth and others for following of profane ſports on the Lords holy-day, to wit, his own day, &amp; many ſuch like outrages they do. Thus they trample upon the holy city, as labouring to deſtroy, and bring into contempt, as it were by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their foule foot upon all holineſſe. Like thoſe wicked and falſe Shepherds in <hi>Ezechiel,</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezech.</hi> 34.18, 19.</note> that <hi>devoure the good paſture, and tread the reſidue under their feet; that drinke of the deepe waters, and foule the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due with their feete,</hi> ſo as the flock of God muſt eate and drink that, which their filthy feete have trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den upon, and fouled.<note n="a" place="margin">Note here good Reader, that the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor writ this before this time of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily in part begun and hopefully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected unto a perfection.</note> Now when was ever the holy City, the true Church of God, in all theſe reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects, more trodden upon with the feete of falſe ſhepherds? when was all holineſſe ever more ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp; deſpiſed, &amp; railed upon &amp; reviled, &amp; perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, &amp; oppreſſed, &amp; trampled upon, then now in our time? that we neede not doubt, but that this is the time of the Sixt Trumpet, under which wee now live. How are the godly and painfull Miniſters of God in <hi>England</hi> miſuſed, their mouths ſtopped, their wives, children, and families diſpoſſeſſed, and caſt out of their habitations, all holy and true profeſſors among the People, vexed, wearied, and even worri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Purſivants, and courts of Prelates? ſo as they are forced many of them to forſake their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and ſweete native country, to go ſeeke for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge among wild beaſts, and wilde Salvages, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:157070:19"/> wilde deſerts,<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.37, 38.</note> 
                  <hi>wandring up and down</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſpeakes) <hi>in deſerts, and in mountains, and in dens and caves of the earth, of whome the world is not worthy, &amp;c.</hi> Thus is not <hi>the holy City trodden under foote of theſe Gentiles,</hi> yea, worſe then the old Gentiles, the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonian</hi> Beaſt, and his broode, having loſt all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, and all the properties of reaſonable men, like<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Nabuchadnezzar,</hi> when he grazed among the beaſts of the field: when nothing will ſatisfie them, but the utter deſolation and extirpation of the Saints of God, and of all holineſſe? What neede then have Gods people to cry, and pray with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83.1, 2, 3, 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Keepe not thou ſilence, o God, hold not thy peace, and be not ſtill, O God. For loe, thine enemies make a tumult, and they that hate thee have lift up the head. They have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken crafty counſell againſt thy people, and conſulted againſt thy hidden ones. They have ſaid, come, let us cut them off from being a Nation, that the name of</hi> Iſraell <hi>may bee no more in remembrance. For they have conſulted together with one conſent, they are confederate againſt Thee. But do thou unto them as unto the</hi> Madianites, <hi>as to</hi> Siſera, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as it followeth to the end of the Pſalme. <hi>Let them be confounded, and troubled for ever: let them be put to ſhame and periſh: that men may know, that thou, whoſe name alone it</hi> Jehovah, <hi>art the moſt high over al the earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.3, 4, 5, 6, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>how long ſhall theſe wicked</hi> thus <hi>triumph? How long ſhall they utter, and ſpeak hard things? and all the workers of iniquitie boaſt themſelves? How long ſhall they breake in pieces thy people, O Lord: and affl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct thine heritage? How long ſhall they ſlay the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow and the ſtranger, and murther the fatherleſſe? How long</hi> ſhall theſe Atheiſts ſay, <hi>The Lord ſhal not ſee, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhal the God of</hi> Jacob <hi>regard it? How long</hi> ſhall
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:157070:20"/> theſe <hi>Gentiles</hi> thus <hi>tread under foot the holy Citie</hi> of our God? It is ſaid here, <hi>Two and forty moneths.</hi> Surely, as the words doe ſound, no very long time. Two and forty moneths make up three yeers and a halfe, and not much more then thoſe thouſand, two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and threeſcore days, in the next Verſe. Now whether theſe forty two moneths be taken literally and ſtrictly, or whether they ſignifie ſome longer or ſhorter time is uncertain to us: this we may certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly build upon, that the time of Antichriſts afflicting of Gods Church, under this Trumpet, ſhall not be long. But this number of forty and two moneths being ſo preciſely laid downe, as containing three yeeres and a halfe, we may be the bolder to take it literally for this ſpace of time. Nor is it unuſuall in Scripture ſo to number, according to the ſtrict let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thereof; as of <hi>Iſraels</hi> affliction in <hi>Egypt,</hi> from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> calling, juſt foure hundred and thirtie yeeres: and the <hi>Jews</hi> Captivitie in <hi>Babylon</hi> juſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty yeeres. And in <hi>Daniel,</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.25.</note> A time, times, and halfe, or part of a time, is taken for three yeers, and part of the fourth, wherein that proud King <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> (who was a type of Antichriſt) ſhould and did afflict the people of God. A time, or times, being interpreted by <hi>Daniel</hi> himſelfe, to bee ſo many<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.13.</note> yeers. The like phraſe whereunto wee have <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel.</hi> 12.14. that the Church ſhould be perſecuted of the Dragon a time, times, and halfe a time. Which is to bee interpreted, according to thoſe times in <hi>Daniel,</hi> three yeers and a halfe. And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon it is, that the Jeſuits, as <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and others, ſtand ſo ſtiffe, that Antichriſts Reigne ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue but three yeeres and a halfe, by which they
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:157070:20"/> think to excuſe the Pope from being Antichriſt. But it will not ſerve their turn. For we eaſily grant, that three yeers and a halfe, being the ſumme of fortie and two moneths, is that ſpace of time, wherein the Beaſt out of the bottomleſſe pit, that Antichriſt, ſhall afflict Gods Church under this ſixt Trumpet. And ſo likewiſe this ſpace of time doth anſwer that time, times, and part of time, wherein <hi>Antiochus</hi> the type of Antichriſt, afflicted the ancient people of God, which was a good part of three yeeres and a halfe, as <hi>Tremelius</hi> well ſheweth in his notes upon <hi>Daniel.</hi> And if we conſider the practices of <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> in that time, and compare them with Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts practices in this ſixt Trumpet, we ſhall find a marvellous correſpondence between them. Now of <hi>Antiochus, Daniel</hi> ſaith,<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan</hi> 7.25.</note> 
                  <hi>He ſhall ſpeak great words againſt the moſt High, and ſhal weare out the Saints of the moſt High, and think to change times and Laws: and they ſhall be given into his hand, untill a time, and times, and the dividing of time.</hi> Whereupon <hi>Tremellius</hi> notes, that this <hi>Antiochus</hi> was moſt blaſphemous againſt God, and a moſt cruell Tyrant over Gods people; in ſo much as he took upon him, and did arrogate unto himſelfe divine authoritie in aboliſhing the Sabbaths, and other Laws of God, and did inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute and impoſe new Laws and Ceremonies accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his owne humour and pleaſure. Now what doth Antichriſt, and his Limbes the Prelates, in theſe our days? Doe they not moſt proudly<note n="i" place="margin">See the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury</hi> his laſt Book through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, toge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>her wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h all his practices.</note> arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate to themſelves divine authoritie, and impiouſly blaſpheme God and Chriſt, in ſaying, Chriſt thought it fitteſt to appoint them as his Viceroys in governing his Church? Doe they not hereupon
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:157070:21"/> beare themſelves as ſo many gods, ſitting in Chriſts throne, impoſing their owne devices, Ceremonies, Canons, upon the conſciences of Gods people? Doe they not vilifie the holy Scripture, as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient and imperfect Rule of Faith, and preferre the Tradition of their prelaticall Church before it? Doe they not abrogate the moralitie of the fourth Commandement, as not binding us Chriſtians to keep the Lords day for our Sabbath day? Do they not diſpenſe with the profanation of it by moſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious and laſcivious Sports and Paſtimes to all youth and others, thereby alſo diſpenſing with the fifth Commandement, when Maſters may not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain their own Servants, nor Parents their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren from their laudable Sports (as they call them) that day? Doe they not forbid Miniſters to preach twice on that day? Doe they not altogether forbid ſound preaching of the doctrines of Grace? And do they not<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.25.</note> 
                  <hi>weare out</hi> (and to uſe their own Phraſe) <hi>worme out</hi> godly Miniſters, and good people, and make havock of all holineſſe (as is noted before) and commit all manner of out-rage and crueltie upon the Servants of God? And this their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream out-rage and crueltie hath continued now very neer three yeers and a halfe, or fortie and two moneths, I ſay the extremitie of it,<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.4.</note> as when they fall to ſhed bloud, &amp;c. though they have been play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their pranks, and laying their plots a long time, but more covertly and inſenſibly, till of later days, the flame of their Antichriſtian outrage hath broke out, ready to ſet all in a combuſtion. But I truſt to ſee the expiration of theſe two and forty moneths to run out very ſhortly. And were there not ſuch a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:157070:21"/> time here limited, yet ſuch hath beene the fury of theſe men, like a hideous ſtorme, or impetuous tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, that it cannot be conceived it ſhould laſt any long time, but quickly run it ſelfe dry, or out of breath. And God being ſo deſperatly and Giantlike provoked, it cannot ſtand with his patience, nor with his honour, to ſuffer long ſuch affronts. And he hath promiſed to<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 18.8.</note> avenge the cauſe of his Elect quickly. And therefore certainly it will not bee long, before he<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 59.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>repay fury to his adverſaries;</hi> and the rather at this time, when the Lord ſees things ſo deſperate, that there is <hi>no man</hi> to <hi>ſtand in the gap,</hi> no interceſſor; but that <hi>truth faileth, and he that departeth from evill, maketh himſelfe a prey; and there is no judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> (as the Prophet there ſpeaks) <hi>therefore his own arme ſhall bring ſalvation, when hee ſhall put on righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe as a breſt-plate, and an helmet of ſalvation upon his head, and the garments of vengeance for clothing, and Zeale as a Cloake.</hi> Thus<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.37, 38.</note> 
                  <hi>he that ſhall come, will come, and will not tarry. Now the juſt ſhall live by faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It followeth, Verſe 3.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>And I will give power unto my two witneſſes, and they ſhall propheſie a thouſand, two hundred, and threeſcore dayes, clothed in ſackcloth.</hi> Here it is to be noted, that during all the hardſhip of Gods people under this ſixt Trumpet, wherein the holy Citie, Chriſts true Church, is trodden under foot by the Spirituall <hi>Babylon,</hi> or by the Beaſt out of the bottomleſſe pit, yet God will not want his wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to propheſie, and teſtifie his truth even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the moſt cruell and bloudy perſecutors ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. And hee will have at the leaſt <hi>two witneſses,</hi> by whoſe teſtimony<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 18.16.</note> 
                  <hi>every word ſhall be eſtabliſhed.</hi> Nor can it be expected, that in ſuch a terrible time,<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Amos</hi> 5.13.</note> 
                  <hi>an
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:157070:22"/> evill time,</hi> wherein the prudent do keep ſilence, there ſhould be many <hi>witneſses</hi> to be found. But that there ſhould be ſome, at the leaſt two, God will raiſe them up, Chriſt will give them power. <hi>I will give</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>power, to my two witneſſes.</hi> To doe what? To <hi>prophecie,</hi> that is, to preach the truth, to witneſſe it againſt all oppoſition, to denounce judgements againſt the Adverſaries, and to comfort Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with his promiſes. As the Prophet <hi>Micah,</hi> ſaith,<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mic.</hi> 3.8, 9. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Truly I am ful of power by the Spirit of the Lord, and of judgement, and of might, to declare unto</hi> Jacob <hi>his tranſgreſsion, and to</hi> Iſrael <hi>his ſinne. Heare this, I pray you, yee Heads of the houſe of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and Princes of the houſe of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>that abhorre judgement, and pervert all equitie. They build up</hi> Sion <hi>with bloud, and</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>with iniquitie. The Heads thereof judge for reward, and the Prieſts thereof teach for hire, and the Prophets therof divine for mony: yet wil they lean upon the Lord, and ſay, Is not the Lord among us? None evil can come upon us. Therefore ſhal</hi> Sion <hi>for your ſake be ploughed as a field, and</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>ſhal become heaps, and the Mountaine of the houſe, as the high places of the foreſt.</hi> Thus the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. Now who is hee that would ſtand up for a witneſſe againſt wicked Prelates, Prieſts, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, againſt wicked Princes and Rulers, againſt wicked Heads and Judges in a forlorne time, as here the Prophet did, except the Lord had firſt filled him with <hi>power, judgement, and might by the Spirit of God?</hi> Therefore ſaith the Lord to <hi>Jeremie,</hi> when he complained, ſaying,<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 15 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Woe is mee, my mother, that thou haſt borne me a man of ſtrife, and a man of contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the whole earth,</hi> &amp;c.<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Why is my paine perpetuall, and my wound incurable, &amp;c?</hi>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 19.20.</note> Therefore, ſaith the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:157070:22"/> Lord, <hi>If thou take forth the precious from the vile, thou ſhalt be as my mouth: Let them returne unto thee, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne thou not unto them. And I will make thee unto this people a fenced brazen wal, and they ſhall fight againſt thee, but they ſhal not prevaile againſt thee: for I am with thee to ſave thee, and to deliver thee, ſaith the Lord. And I wil deliver thee out of the hand of the wicked, and I wil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme thee out of the hand of the terrible.</hi> And <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Lord ſpake thus to me, with a ſtrong hand, and inſtructed me, that I ſhould not walk in the way of this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, nor to make a confederacie with them.</hi> Thus there. And thus here the Lord gives <hi>power</hi> to his <hi>two wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſses to propheſie,</hi> and beare teſtimony againſt the wicked and terrible enemies of his Church here under the Sixt Trumpet.</p>
               <p>In the next place is ſet down the time how long theſe two witneſſes ſhall propheſie, and that is, a <hi>thouſand, two hundred, and threeſcore days.</hi> And this anſweres to the forty and two moneths of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts oppreſsing of gods people, which is three yeeres and a halfe. For a thouſand, two hundred, and threeſcore dayes, make up (within one weeke) juſt three yeers and a halfe. So as their prophecy continueth during the great affliction of Gods Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple under this Sixt Trumpet. Whence we may note, here, God never leaves his people in affliction without comfort, nor his truth without teſtimony, nor his adverſaries without conviction, but he ſends his witneſſes to propheſie eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in moſt forlorn times.</p>
               <p>Then follows here the eſtate and condition of theſe two witneſſes, expreſſed by their outward ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, they are <hi>cloathed in ſackcloth;</hi> ſutable to <hi>Elias,</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt. And ſutable to their habit was
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:157070:23"/> their prophecying, preaching repentance, and remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſins to the penitent, and believers, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing judgments to the obſtinate. And as was their habit, ſuch were their affections, men crucified to the World, forſaking all, and accounting all things to be loſſe, and betaking themſelves to their Sackcloth. It was no time now, as the Lord ſaith to <hi>Ieremie,</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.5.5.</note> to ſeeke great things to themſelves.</p>
               <p>It followeth, Verſe 4.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Theſe are the two Olive-trees, and the two Candleſticks, ſtanding before the God of the Earth.</hi> In theſe words is couched a great myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and a great worke ſignified, which the Lord is about to doe in the time of this Sixt Trumpet. For the finding out whereof, we are to compare theſe words with that prophecie which we finde written in the fourth Chapter of <hi>Zechariah,</hi> where (Ver. 1.) the prophet is by the angell awaked as out of ſleep. Which noteth a ſtirring up of the Prophet to great attention to what was now in a viſion ſhewed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, as being a matter of great moment, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently to bee marked. In the viſion the prophet Saw a <hi>golden Candelſtick</hi> with <hi>Seven Lamps,</hi> and <hi>on each ſide thereof two Olive trees.</hi> This viſion came in the time when the Temple at <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> was a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring by <hi>Zerubbabell,</hi> and it was by the word of the Lord to ſignify unto him (as V. 6.) Saying, <hi>This is the word of the Lord unto</hi> Zerubbabel, <hi>ſaying, Not by might, nor by power, but by my Spirit, ſaith the Lord of hoſts.</hi> This was to comfort and incourage <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> in the work (as alſo Verſe 9.) which the enemies of Gods people did ſo much deride and mock at, as a worke which could never be finiſhed; as we read, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 4.2, 3. Where <hi>Sanballat</hi> ſpake to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:157070:23"/> his brethren, and the army of <hi>Samaria,</hi> having great indignation, and mocking the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſaid, <hi>What do theſe feeble Iews? Wil they fortifie themſelves? Wil they ſacrifiſe? Wil they make an end in a day? Wil they revive the ſtones out of the heaps of the rubbiſh which are burnt?</hi> And <hi>Tobiah</hi> the <hi>Ammonite</hi> ſaid, <hi>Even that which they build, if a Fox go up, he ſhal eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> break down their ſtone wal.</hi> Now againſt all this the Lord incourageth <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> and his people by this Viſion of the Candleſticks, and two Olive-trees ſhewed to the Prophet, whereof the Lord himſelfe is the Authour, and not man. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, he ſaith, <hi>Not by might, nor by power, but by my Spirit, ſaith the Lord of hoſts.</hi> That like as the Spirit of the Lord ſhewed this Viſion to his Prophet, wherein is ſhadowed out the indeficient and never fayling Kingdome of Jeſus Chriſt, who is the fountain of grace, and the good<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ro.</hi> 11.17, 24</note> Olive-tree, which runneth and floweth forth with Oile continually to ſupply his<note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.</note> golden Candleſticks, his Miniſters and Prophets, by the light of whoſe Prophecie (as the Temple was founded and finiſhed by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie of <hi>haggai</hi> and <hi>Zechariah</hi> the Prophets of the Lord at that time: ſo) the Church of Chriſt, in all ages ſhall be built up, repaired, and in fine fully fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. But in ſpeciall this worke, this great worke of repayring the Temple, and reſtoring true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion unto its primitive purity, is to be accompliſhed under this ſixt Trumpet, wherein the Lord hath his two witneſſes (anſwerable to thoſe two Prophets, <hi>Haggai,</hi> and <hi>Zechariah,</hi> by whoſe Prophecie the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Temple, the figure of the Church under the Goſpel, was repaired) by the power of whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie, through the Grace and Spirit of Chriſt,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:157070:24"/> his true Church and Religion ſhall bee repaired, maugre all the malice of <hi>Sanballat,</hi> and <hi>Tobiah,</hi> with their <hi>Samaritan</hi> Army, to withſtand the building, and notwithſtanding all the ſcorne and mockerie, power and policie of Antichriſt, and his nimble Foxes, that thinke by their treading upon the wall to overthrow it. This work (I ſay) is to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and is now already begun to be acted under this Sixt Trumpet. And therefore, hath the Spirit of Chriſt in this place compared his two witneſſes, and their prophecie, unto two golden Candleſticks, and two Olive-trees that ſtand before<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Zech.</hi> 4.14.</note> the Lord of the whole Earth, as it is ſaid in <hi>Zechariah:</hi> as it were pointing us with the finger to that whole viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Prophet, ſetting forth the perfect repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Temple; to the end wee might be out of all doubt that the Lord, under this Trumpet, is about the like great work of reparation, and reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his Church and Religion, which ſhall proſper and be accompliſhed <hi>not by might, nor by power of men,</hi> but <hi>by the Spirit of the Lord</hi> in the mouth of his <hi>two witneſſes,</hi> and by the word of their <hi>prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,</hi> crying (as in <hi>Zechariah</hi>)<note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>Zech.</hi> 4 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Grace, grace unto it.</hi> And for our further confirmation in the truth hereof, have wee not a cleere and evident demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of it in that admirable worke of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Kirke of <hi>Scotland</hi> at this day, whereof we are all eye-witneſſes? And was this done <hi>by might and power of man?</hi> No. They indeed (as<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Neh.</hi> 4 17, 18</note> thoſe <hi>Jewiſh</hi> builders and repayrers, as aforeſaid) began to build, working with the one hand, &amp; with the other holding a weapon, or having their ſword at their ſide, to defend themſelves againſt the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:157070:24"/> yoke of the Herarchie, as againſt <hi>Sanballets</hi> and <hi>Tobiahs;</hi> and chiefly to vindicate the honour, crown, throne, Scepter, and Kingdome of Jeſus Chriſt over his people from Antichriſts proud and impious uſurpations, which all Chriſtian Princes and people are bound to doe: as alſo they had their Prophets, with publike faſting &amp; prayer (ſuch as the <hi>Jews</hi> alſo uſed at the repairing of the Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they ſo proſpered, and God gave them ſuch fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour in the eies of their Sovereign, that they altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther laid aſide their weapons, and ſo <hi>not by might, nor by power, but by the Grace of God,</hi> that great work (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all their adverſaries plotting and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring againſt it) was in ſome good meaſure ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, to the everlaſting honour and prayſe of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, and to the renowne of that King, the Lords Anointed, whoſe heart was moved to become the Lords great Inſtrument in permitting, and aſſenting unto ſo glorious a worke; whereby as Chriſts Kingdome and Temple is now in a faire way reſtored and eſtabliſhed in that Nation, and freed from Antichriſts yoake: So the Kings throne alſo is eſtabliſhed in that Kingdome, and ſhal be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the comming of Jeſus Chriſt, by whom alone<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Kings do reigne, and Princes decree juſtice.</hi> And as the Lord hath thus begun his great &amp; glorious work of repayring his Temple, and reſtoring Religion, ſo evidently repreſented before our eyes, as in a moſt cleere Viſion, in this ſixt Trumpet, as hath beene ſhewed by comparing this Prophecie with that in <hi>Zechariah</hi> aforeſaid: ſo certainly the Lord will fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his own worke in other Kingdoms alſo where both Princes and people are deluded, and brought
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:157070:25"/> into (at leaſt) Spirituall bondage under the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian yoake, which though it be curiouſly pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and guilded over, and as it were faced and lined with Phariſaicall broad <hi>Phylacteries,</hi> woven with goodly words, As, The Church, moſt Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, holy Hierarchie, Chriſts Vice roys, and the like pompous and pretended titles, yet theſe be but golden chains, and ſilken cords, purple coloured, wherein to lead captive even Kingdoms and States, to make up the traine of Antichriſts triumph.</p>
               <p>And here, for a cloſe of this excellent Prophecy in this fourth Verſe, give mee leave to relate a true ſtory. My ſelfe having certaine yeers agone publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in print, and that alſo by Authority, an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer (entitled, The Bayting of the Popes Bull) to a Bull of Pope <hi>Vrban</hi> the eighth, which paſſed up and down in <hi>England,</hi> inciting his <hi>Roman</hi> Catholikes to ſtand for the Catholike Cauſe: and having ſet in the Frontiſpiece of the Book, a Picture, repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing King <hi>Charles,</hi> with a ſword in his hand, the point whereof was directed ſo, as it put off the Popes tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Crowne in the other picture over againſt it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting the Pope, with Verſes interpreting the ſame: and having a young daughter then of three or foure yeeres old at moſt, to whom I (my wife holding the child in her armes) ſhewed this picture, interpreting the ſame unto her: the childe preſently thereupon replyed, O Father, <hi>Our King ſhall cut off the Popes head: Jt muſt be ſo, Jt muſt be ſo.</hi> And this ſo redoubled, ſhe ſpake with ſuch an extraordinary vigor and vivacitie or quickneſſe of ſpirit, and utterance, as both my ſelfe and wife were ſtruck with great admiration. Now if a man ſhould have ſaid then, when this was
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:157070:25"/> uttered, that ſuch a ſpeech, proceeding ſo ſtrangely from a child was ſure ſome Prophecie inſpired into her by Gods Spirit, of what ſhould after come to paſſe, would have found but a few to give credit thereunto, but rather would have beene laughed to ſcorn. Although I preſently thereupon ſaid to my wife, ſurely this in time may prove to be a true Prophecie; God is able to bring it to paſſe, though never ſo unlikely. But now that wee ſee the Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchie utterly raced and rooted out of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and that by King <hi>Charles</hi> his Royall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, ratifying the ſame in Parliament: tell mee, what think yee? Was not here a cutting off of the Popes head by the King, as touching his Kingdome of <hi>Scotland?</hi> For is not the Popes headſhip upheld in chiefe in the Prelates, and Hierarchie? Might not then the childes ſpeech be a Prophecie, being thus far verified in ſo great and unexpected a work as this? And if ſo, why may it not reach to be a like verified in cutting off the Popes head alſo in <hi>England,</hi> as it is now in <hi>Scotland?</hi> Is any thing hard to the<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 21.1.</note> Lord, who hath the Kings heart in his hand, <hi>as the rivers of waters, turning it whitherſoever hee will?</hi> But for this we muſt patiently wait, and inceſſantly pray, that the Lord will bring to paſſe his owne counſell, and finiſh his worke thus begun, and that Antichriſts Throne and Kingdome being throwne downe and deſtroyed, Chriſt alone may reigne in the hearts and conſciences of his people, and the Kings Crowne may ever flouriſh and ſhine forth in the beauty of abundance of peace and proſperitie, till time ſhall be no more. Nay, whither the child propheſied, or no: here we have a moſt ſure word
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:157070:26"/> of Prophecie, which tels us what Chriſt is now a working, namely, the great Reformation of his Church, and Reſtauration of Religion, which as he hath ſo gloriouſly begun to doe in <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſo I truſt hee will ſhew the like mercie to <hi>England,</hi> (though a ſinfull Nation) in rooting out thoſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked limbes of the Beaſt, by whom Religion, and the whole Land is ſo of late, more than ever before ſince Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> dayes, defiled. Yea, wee may be as ſure hereof, as wee are ſure this is Gods Word, that the Lord will, and that very ſpeedily, ſo finiſh this worke now begun, within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of this ſixt Trumpet, as not all the power and policie of Antichriſt and his Confederates ſhall be able either to prevent it, or ever to overthrow it. For Chriſts Word here muſt needs bee fulfilled, which ſaith, <hi>Theſe are the two Olive-trees, and the two Candleſticks, which ſtand before the GOD of the earth:</hi> As if hee had ſaid, <hi>Even as the viſion of the golden Candleſtick, and of the two Olive-trees on each ſide thereof, ſtanding before the Lord of the whole earth, was ſhewed unto the Prophet</hi> Zechariah; <hi>to be a word of the Lord to incourage</hi> Zerubbabel <hi>the Prince, and the people of God in repayring and finiſhing of the Temple in</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>then in hand, which the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of</hi> Judah <hi>reſiſted and withſtood with all their might and malice, but were not able to fruſtrate the worke: So I have here purpoſely named my two witneſſes the two Olive-trees, and the two Candleſticks ſtanding before the God of the earth, that it may be the like viſion (as it were) to my people living under the ſixt Trumpet to encourage them not only to begin, but to proceed to the finiſhing and perfecting of the worke of Reformation of Religion, and reſtauration
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:157070:26"/> of my ſpirituall Temple, the Church; and though the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries be potent, and labour tooth and naile to hinder the worke, and my people are weake: yet know, that it is</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Zechar</hi> 4.7.</note> 
                  <hi>not by might, or by power, but by my Spirit, ſaith the Lord of hoſts. For</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 46 10.</note> 
                  <hi>my Counſell ſhall ſtand, and I will do all my pleaſure. And as for thine enemies, O my people, feare them not, but ſay unto them,</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 8.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Take counſell together, and it ſhall come to naught: Speake the word, and it ſhall not ſtand: for God is with us. And I ſay to thee, O my people, Behold,</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 54.16, 17.</note> 
                  <hi>I have created the Smith, that bloweth the coals in the fire, and that bringeth forth an Inſtrument for his worke, and I have created the waſter to deſtroy. No weapon that is formed againſt thee, ſhall proſper, and every tongue that ſhal riſe againſt thee in judgment, thou ſhalt condemn. This is the heritage of the ſervants of the Lord, and their righteouſneſse is of me, ſaith the Lord.</hi> And thus much of this Verſe.</p>
               <p>Now follows Verſe 5.6.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 5.6.</note> 
                  <hi>And if any man ſhal hurt them, fire proceedeth out of their mouth, and devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth their enemies: and if any man wil hurt them, he muſt in this manner be killed. Theſe have power to ſhut heaven, that it rain not in the dayes of their prophecie: and have power over waters, to turn them into bloud, and to ſmite the earth with all plagues, as often as they wil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In theſe two Verſes is ſet forth the efficacie of that <hi>power,</hi> which Chriſt giveth to his <hi>two witneſſes</hi> in their prophecying. And this <hi>power</hi> is ſuch, as that of <hi>Elias,</hi> and that of <hi>Moſes</hi> was. For firſt, here is an alluſion to the <hi>power and ſpirit of</hi> Elias, in the fifth Verſe, wherein this ſpeech is redou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled: thus, <hi>If any man ſhal hurt them, fire procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth out of their mouth, and devoureth their enemies: and if any man wil hurt them, he muſt in this manner be killed.</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:157070:27"/> How is that?<note n="h" place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Elias</hi> we know, when the firſt Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain with his 50 men were ſent to fetch him by force to King <hi>Ahaziah,</hi> ſaying unto him, <hi>Thou man of God, the King hath ſaid, come downe:</hi> anſwered, <hi>If I be a man of God, then let fire come downe from heaven and conſume thee, and thy fifty. And there came down fire from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and conſumed him, and his fifty.</hi> And the like be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell the ſecond Captain, and his fifty. Thus <hi>fire came out of</hi> Elias <hi>his mouth,</hi> and it conſumed or devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his enemies. And this was done twice. Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, here it is twice repeated, <hi>If any man hurt them, &amp;c.</hi> Now by fire comming out of their mouth, is not meant literally, that fire proceedeth out of their mouth: but that, as <hi>Elias</hi> by his word brought fire down from Heaven, wherin his Word took effect: ſo the judgments, which theſe two witneſſes ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce againſt their injurious adverſaries, the impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable &amp; furious enemies of Gods Church, that will not be brought by the word of their prophecie to repentance, ſhall as certainly come to paſſe, and fall upon them to their deſtruction, as that fire did fall from Heaven upon thoſe men, according to <hi>Elias</hi> his word. I ſay, if they repent not. For the third Captaine with his fiftie, we ſee humbled himſelfe, and intreated <hi>Elias,</hi> ſo as <hi>Elias</hi> went with him to the King; but being come, what judgement hee denounced againſt that wicked idolatrous King, fell upon him alſo, that hee died of his ſickneſſe. And in this reſpect Gods Word in the mouth of his Prophets is compared to a <hi>fire;</hi> ſo as he that reſiſts this word, is as the fooliſh fly, that flappeth againſt the flaming of the Candle, and ſo is conſumed in the flame. And the like manner of ſpeech the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:157070:27"/> uſeth elſwhere. As <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Repent, or elſe I will come unto thee quickly, and will fight againſt thee with the ſword of my mouth.</hi> And Chap. 19.21. <hi>And the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant were ſlaine with the ſword of him that ſate upon the horſe, which ſword proceeded out of his mouth.</hi> Which is all one with that ſpeech, 2 <hi>Theſs.</hi> 2.8. <hi>And then ſhall that wicked one be revealed, whom the Lord ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume with the ſpirit of his mouth.</hi> So wee ſee what is here meant by the fire, whith proceedeth out of the mouth of theſe two witneſſes; And this word, <hi>If any man hurt them,</hi> in the originall it is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is. <hi>If any man will doe them injury,</hi> or <hi>offer them violence</hi> againſt all law and equitie: <hi>fire pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth out of their mouth, and devoureth their enemies:</hi> that is, the word of their prophecie ſhall bring as certaine deſtruction upon their injurious enemies, as <hi>Elias</hi> his word brought fire from Heaven upon thoſe that were ſent to take him. And therefore the word is here doubled (as before is noted) for the certainty of it, as was<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.</note> 
                  <hi>Pharaohs</hi> dream.</p>
               <p>Againe, it is ſaid here, <hi>Theſe have power to ſhut heaven, that it raine not in the dayes of their prophecie.</hi> This alſo alludes to <hi>Elias,</hi> whoſe word of prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie did ſhut up the heavens, that it rained not for the ſpace of three yeers and a halfe, in the time of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habs</hi> Reigne. So as here again is ſet forth the power of theſe two witneſſes prophecie, in bringing judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon the Land, where Gods Word is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and entertained in that love and reſpect as it ought to bee, but that the witneſſes, even for no other cauſe, but the words ſake, which they propheſie, are injuriouſly and violently handled againſt all Law and juſtice, yea, and all humanity,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:157070:28"/> in all beſt iall crueltie. And therefore no marvail, if in the time of their prophecie being thus evill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated, manifold judgments in ſundry kindes doe fall upon a Land, as the Sword, Famine, Peſtilence, or the like. Yea, and if God ſend extraordinary foule weather in an extreame abundance of a long continued raine, and that againſt harveſt, as we have ſeen lately this very laſt Summer in <hi>England,</hi> ſo as the harveſt ſuffered much damage thereby: it were good, that they ſhould enquire, and conſider what is the cauſe, that hath ſo of late provoked God to ſend forth from Heaven ſo many tokens of his wrath and indignation, threatning even deſolation to the whole Land, if they repent not. Are there no witneſſes abroad at this time? Or hath not <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> defiled it ſelf with the violent and lawleſſe cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty of ſhedding the innocent bloud of ſome at leaſt of Chriſts witneſſes? If it be ſo, as <hi>England</hi> can neither waſh her hands from the guilt, nor ſtop the eares of Heaven from the hideous cry of that inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent bloud: no marvail, I ſay, if <hi>England</hi> be many wayes plagued. For theſe witneſſes have power to ſhut Heaven, that it raine not in the dayes of their prophecie, as <hi>Elias</hi> did.</p>
               <p>Not only ſo, But they have alſo power over <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to turne them to bloud, and to ſmite the earth with all plagues, as often as they wil.</hi> Theſe words have an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion to <hi>Moſes,</hi> as we ſaid before; Who in <hi>Egypt</hi> had power given him of God with his Rod to turn their <hi>waters into bloud,</hi> and ſo ſmite the Land with manifold plagues. And here ſeemes to be more couched, then ſo, in this parallell of theſe two wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes power, to that of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron.</hi> For the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:157070:28"/> words here imply thus much, that as thoſe many <hi>Plagues,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> 
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> brought upon <hi>Egypt</hi> by his <hi>Rod</hi> &amp; word of prophecy, were ſo many forerunners of the utter deſolation of hard-hearted <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> &amp; his ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate <hi>Egyptians,</hi> who would not ſuffer <hi>Gods people to go ſacrifice to the Lord their God:</hi> So thoſe many tokens of Gods wrath, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> have bin powred upon <hi>England</hi> of late days, for their ſore afflicting &amp; oppreſſing of Gods people by the Prelats and their officers, thoſe <hi>Egyptian</hi> Taskmaſters, &amp; not ſuffering them to enjoy that freedom &amp; liberty of conſcience, which Chriſt hath by his precious bloud purchaſed for them, but holding their noſes to the Grind-ſtone (as wee ſay) and enſlaving them to the <hi>Egyptian</hi> tasks in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of thoſe many Popiſh Ceremonies ſo ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannically impoſed and preſſed upon them; as alſo for that moſt impious crying downe of the Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the Sabbath, and ſtopping Miniſters mouthes for preaching the ſincere Word of God, throwing them out of their Miniſtery, and many ſuch like, worſe then <hi>Egyptian</hi> out-rages, and ſuch as were never done in any Chriſtian State ſince the Apoſtles times to this preſent: thoſe tokens (I ſay) doe plainly ſhew, that without ſpeedy repentance, and a thorow reformation of theſe intolerable ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, God will certainly bring the Taskmaſters to deſolation, and in the ſame ſea of deſtruction to the <hi>Egyptians</hi> will make a way for his peoples liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie from that <hi>Egyptian</hi> bondage, wherein they have been ſo long, ſo miſerably captived. Nor let it ſeeme ſtrange, that I match <hi>Englands</hi> Taskmaſters with thoſe of <hi>Egypt;</hi> for by and by wee ſhall find a ſpirituall <hi>Egypt,</hi> wherof that in <hi>England</hi> will hardly acquit it ſelfe from being apart, or party at leaſt, if
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:157070:29"/> all circumſtances be but well weighed. And ſo we paſſe to the Verſes following.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 7.</note>Verſe 7. <hi>And when they ſhall have finiſhed their te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie, the beaſt that aſcendeth out of the bottomleſſe pit, ſhall make war againſt them, and ſhall overcome them, and kill them, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="50-93" type="pages">
               <p>Here begins a battaile, wherein three circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are obſervable: 1 The time when it begins: 2 The parties, or warriers: and 3 the iſſue of the battaile. Firſt, for the time, it is, when <hi>the two wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſses have finiſhed their teſtimony.</hi> Then, and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Till then, the Beaſt hath no power to ſet upon them. Thus it was with the Captain of our ſalvation, <hi>John</hi> 7.8. <hi>My time,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is not yet come.</hi> And, Verſe 30. when his enemies ſought to take him, <hi>no man laid hands on him, becauſe his houre was not yet come.</hi> But when his houre was come, that hee muſt lay down his life (as <hi>John</hi> 13.1. and 17.1) and when hereupon his enemies came to take him, <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith unto them,<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 22.53.</note> 
                  <hi>This is your houre and power of darkneſſe.</hi> Till now, they had no power, till his houre was come. And when upon the Croſſe hee came to ſay, <hi>It is finiſhed,</hi> then, and not before, <hi>hee gave up the ghoſt.</hi> Thus he <hi>finiſhed his Teſtimony</hi> before his death. It is ſaid of <hi>David,</hi> that<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 13 36.</note> 
                  <hi>after hee had ſerved his owne Generation by the will of GOD, hee fell aſleep.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of himſelf,<note n="m" place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.6, 7</note> 
                  <hi>I am now ready to bee offered, and the time of my depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is at hand.</hi> And the reaſon is added in the next Verſe. <hi>I have fought a good fight, J have finiſhed my courſe.</hi> Thus when theſe <hi>two witneſſes have finiſhed their teſtimony,</hi> the Beaſt ſets upon them, and kils them. And here let me give you a moſt remarkable inſtance, wherein God is the more glorified.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:157070:29"/> Which at that very time, when it was done, was obſerved by ſome neighbour Miniſters in <hi>London.</hi> Only this I deprecate, that none doe imput<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unto me any vain humour of glorying, as if I made my ſelfe one of thoſe witneſſes here ſpoken of, ſuch an honour I aſſume not to my ſelfe. Only (I ſay) I crave leave to relate a truth. It is this. I having been<note n="n" place="margin">See a nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble parallel hereof in <hi>Ezech. Chap</hi> 3.24, 25, 26.</note> ſhut up in my owne houſe, by the Prelates Purſuivants daily and hourely watching for mee at my gates, the ſpace of almoſt two moneths, in which time, notwithſtanding their continuall rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and ringing at my gates, I was a compiling my Book of two Sermons, which I had preached in my Church the fifth of <hi>November</hi> then laſt paſt; &amp; fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it for the Preſs, that ſo it might be a <hi>teſtimony</hi> to all the World of that truth, which I had therein de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, and for which I was then queſtioned and troubled by the Prelates: the which <hi>teſtimony,</hi> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo my <hi>Apologie for my Appeale,</hi> being now <hi>finiſhed,</hi> and fully printed, and ſome Books for the King and Councell bound up and brought unto me, the ſame day at night (and not before) came from the Lord of <hi>London,</hi> then Lord Treaſurer, a Serjant at Arms, with a number of Purſuivants and Officers with ſwords and ſtaves, in the evening, and with great violence aſſaulted my doors, and brake them open, though very ſtrong, and ſo came and ſeized on my body, ſitting, with my family, in my gowne, and making no reſiſtance at all. This I thought here not unfit to be noted, as not altogether impertinent to this Prophecie, to which this example may ſeem to have ſome correſpondence. And ſo much of the time, when this warre begins; even when theſe two
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:157070:30"/> witneſſes have finiſhed their teſtimony, and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. The Beaſt, for all his roaring, yet hath not the power to ſet his paw upon Chriſts witneſſes, untill they have finiſhed their teſtimony. And is it not lawfull for me to adde one truth more, that God may be glorified, and the hearts of his people raiſed up, and filled with rejoycing in him? This it is. Not all the Beaſts hundred eyes, not all his quick-ſented bloud-hounds, the Purſuivants, for all their vigilant and eagre hunting, could find out, or diſcover, where this teſtimony (to wit, For God and the King) was printed, though they left never a Printing houſe about <hi>London</hi> unſearched over and over, day by day, the Lord in his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence preſerving not only my perſon, but my te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony alſo, that it ſhould not be prevented, but come forth into the open light.</p>
               <p>It followeth: When they had finiſhed their te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, <hi>The Beaſt that aſcendeth out of the bottomleſſe pit begins to make warre againſt them,</hi> as I have told you before. Here then wee are to conſider the ſecond circumſtance of this warre, the two adverſe parties, the one, the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> &amp;c. the other, the <hi>two witneſſes:</hi> the <hi>Beaſt</hi> is the <hi>Aſsailant,</hi> and the <hi>two Wittneſſes</hi> are the <hi>Defendants.</hi> For the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> hee is here deſcribed from the place whence he comes, the <hi>bottomleſse pit:</hi> and ſecondly, by the manner of his iſſuing thence, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, hee <hi>aſcendeth out of the bottomleſſe pit.</hi> His riſe is groundleſſe, bottomleſſe, out of the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe deep, and his motion is Aſcendant, yea <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, aſcending (being a participle of the preſent tenſe) ſtill aſpiring with<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Lucifer,</hi> to place his throne <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the ſtars,</hi> yea, <hi>above God</hi> himſelfe. Hee is ever
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:157070:30"/> aſcending, but ſtill out of the <hi>bottomleſse pit,</hi> as if hee could never get out of it. This <hi>bottomleſſe pit</hi> is hell, the Den, where this <hi>Beaſt</hi> is bred, and whence he is nouriſhed. And who this <hi>Beaſt</hi> is, yee may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily know, by his Picture lively pourtrayed, Chap. 13. and 17. compared together. He hath his ſeven heads and ten horns: <hi>Monſtrum horrendum, ingens:</hi> the like Beaſt again is not in all the World. And the <hi>Dragon,</hi> the Devil, gives him power, Chap. 13.2. and Verſe 5. <hi>Power is given him to make warre with the Saints, and to overcome them.</hi> The very ſame <hi>Beaſt</hi> here, which maketh warre with Chriſts <hi>wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> and <hi>overcomes</hi> them. This is that <hi>Beaſt</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> plainly deſcribed, Chap. 17. And as this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven-headed, and ten-horned <hi>Beaſt,</hi> hath his aſcent, riſe, and originall out of the bottomleſſe pit: ſo alſo his brood and off-ſpring, as thoſe <hi>Locuſts,</hi> Chap. 9.3. who are this Beaſts Warriers. Thus wee ſee who this Beaſt is, from whence &amp; whither he aſcendeth.</p>
               <p>Now let us ſee what he doth. 1 he <hi>makes warre</hi> againſt the <hi>two witneſſes.</hi> 2 He <hi>overcomes them.</hi> 3 he <hi>killeth them.</hi> Firſt, hee makes warre againſt them. Alas poore witneſſes, for ſuch a great and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Beaſt, with his numerous brood, to make warre againſt them. Such a power to make warre againſt two? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut by this time Chriſts witneſſes may be increaſed, and multiplied to a greater number, and that by the example of the two here ſpoken of, whoſe more eminent and mighty teſtimonies can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſo goe alone, but they will draw many others after them, to teſtifie the ſame truth. Though it pleaſed the Holy Ghoſt to point out but <hi>two witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> only, and in ſuch wiſe to ſet them forth, as there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:157070:31"/> we might come to know the full intent and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this Prophecie, as hath been ſhewed. Now the Beaſt having muſtered his forces together, makes warre againſt the two witneſſes; not only againſt Them, but againſt all other whom hee finds endued with the ſame ſpirit, namely, ſuch as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie againſt the Beaſt and his Throne, and all thoſe, that by their conſtant profeſſion of the Truth, and refuſing communion with the Beaſt, doe become thereby the witneſſes of Chriſt. For the <hi>Beaſt wars with the Saints.</hi> Chap. 13.7.</p>
               <p>But what be thoſe weapons, and what thoſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, wherewith this Beaſt warreth againſt Chriſts witneſſes, and Gods Saints? Surely, hee uſeth all manner of weapons whereby to execute his beaſtly cruelty. And theſe may be reduced to two kindes: The Spirituall Sword: and the Temporall Sword. His Spirituall Sword is the brute Thunderbolt of his execrable Excommunication, direfull Curſes, and dreadfull Courts, as his Court of Inquiſition, and of High Commiſſion, and other his Prelaticall and Hierarchicall Courts, which are ſo many Dens, wherin this hideous Beaſt once incloſing the Saints, doth prey upon them, he and his Cubs. But if this his Sword prove not ſtrong enough as meeting with ſome mettle too tough for it to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>rce, then he can command with a wet finger the helpe of the Temporall Sword, which is like <hi>Tamberlains</hi> black and bloudy Banner, which being diſplayed by the Beaſts power, and inſpired with his fiery-mettled ſpirit, breathes nothing, but either fire and faggot, or Pillory, with ſhedding of bloud, perpetuall cloſe impriſonment, baniſhment, and all other evils of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:157070:31"/> this life, more bitter and cruell, by many degrees, than death it ſelfe. And this is his kinde of warre. But how comes he to do theſe things by the help of the Temporall Power, when commonly all his proceedings are without either law, or colour of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, except according to the Beaſts owne lawleſſe Law? For this, hee wants not his devices: for hee will ſo contrive the matter, and lay his ſnares, as either the innocent (being brought into the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Court, where alſo he himſelf wil ſit a Judge, and where his ſpirit is wondrouſly predominant) ſhall be forced to aſſent to the condemnation of his own cauſe before the hearing: or elſe, if hee refuſe ſo to doe, he ſhall be cenſured as guiltie of all thoſe hainous crimes laid to his charge, though never ſo falſe and maliciouſly deviſed; yea, hee can ſo han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle the buſineſſe, as the cenſure ſhall be agreed upon, and concluded, before ever his day of hearing come, and when it is come, his Legall Defence ſhal never be heard. This needs no application. And this is the Beaſts manner of warring, right; nor ſhould it be properly the Beaſts warre, were it not altogether beſtiall, void of all Law, or conſcience, or honeſty, or humanitie. And ever his mayn for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and battery are bent againſt the two witneſſes, namely ſuch as doe conſtantly teſtifie and maintain the Prerogative of Chriſts Kingly Government o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his Church againſt the Beaſts proud and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall uſurpations; and the truth of the Goſpel and Word of Chriſt, againſt all Antichriſts lyes: and the authoritie and ſufficiencie of the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture againſt the Beaſts unwritten Traditions, and Eccleſiaſticall Canons, the authoritie whereof hee
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:157070:32"/> preferreth above, and oppoſeth againſt the Law of God. As for all wicked, prophane, and impious perſons, his Holines hath no quarrell againſt them; for either they are ſuch, as belong to the Beaſts Den, or at leaſt, though they be not of it, yet they are not much againſt it. Thus he warreth.</p>
               <p>Secondly, as the Beaſt warreth againſt the witneſſes, ſo hee ſhall overcome them. How ſhall hee overcome them? Their faith and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony hee ſhall not overcome, ſo as to force them to recant, or deſert their cauſe, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray their conſcience. For (Chap. 12.11.) thoſe on Chriſts ſide overcame the <hi>Dragon, by the bloud of the Lamb, and by the word of their Teſtimonie, and they loved not their lives unto the death.</hi> Nor ſhal the Beaſt be able to overcome them by force of arguments and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning: for he is a Beaſt, yea, the Beaſt of all Beaſts; his Arguments are fire and faggot, Pillory and bloud-ſhed (as before) down-right club-law, or a puſh with his ten<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.12.</note> hornes, or a by-back-blow with his paw. So as thus hee comes to get the conqueſt over their bodies indeed, he can ſhut them cloſe up, hee can pillory them, hee can mangle and torture them, and a thouſand ways ſubdue<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.28</note> their bodies, but can doe no more. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.4.</p>
               <p>Not only ſo, but (in the third place) hee ſhall kill them. Famous is the Beaſt for his infinite bloudy victories over Chriſts Witneſſes in this kinde, by putting them to death. But now there is a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold kind of death, which he puts them to. The firſt is, by a violent ſeparation of their ſoule from their bodie; as in the flames of Martyrdome. This hath bin the Beaſts practice of old. But this ſubtile
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:157070:32"/> Dragon, finding by experience, that his kingdome rather ſuffered damage this way, then wonne any ground, and that it proved rather an advantage to his Adverſaries, and brought much hatred to his barbarous cruelty in ſo putting them to death: hee hath found out another kinde of death, and that, though not in ſhow, yet indeed farre more cruell than the other; and that is, by a violent and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſeparation of a living man from all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, comforts and contentments in the World, from his wife and children, from his meanes and livelihood, friends and acquaintance, from the Communion of Saints, yea, from all ſocietie of men, and in a word, from all the means of comfort in this life, Spirituall, or Temporall. So as a man in this caſe may be ſaid to be killed, or deprived of life, when he is deprived of all thoſe things, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which life cannot well be called a life, but a death rather, or ſuch a life, as that in hell, where not one drop of comfort is allowed to thoſe tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented ſouls. And as dead men neither ſee, nor heare, nor ſpeake, nor write, nor have any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with the living: So theſe may neither ſee their living friends, nor heare from them by let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, nor ſpeake, nor write unto them, nor have any commerce with them. Thus far dead they be. And in this ſenſe we have ſeen ſome eminent Witneſſes of Chriſt (yet living in their cloſe Priſons in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Lands) thus to bee killed in theſe our dayes. Which being ſo, may it not bee one evident ſigne, that we are now in the ſixt Trumpet, wherein wee have ſeene ſo many things to be come to paſſe and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:157070:33"/> fulfilled, ſo particularly ſet forth in this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie.</p>
               <p>It followeth, Verſe 8.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 8.</note> 
                  <hi>And their dead bodies ſhall lie in the ſtreet of the great Citie, which ſpiritually is called</hi> Sodome <hi>and</hi> Egypt, <hi>where alſo our Lord was crucified. And they of the people, and kindreds, and tongues, and Nations, ſhall ſee their dead bodies three dayes and a halfe, and ſhall not ſuffer their dead bodies to be put in graves: And they that dwell upon the earth ſhall rejoyce over them, and make merry, and ſhall ſend gifts one to another, becauſe theſe two Prophets tormented them that dwelt on the earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now theſe dead bodies (as we ſaid before) may be ſo called, in reſpect of a civill death, as dead to the whole World in a civill reſpect, having no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion nor commerce with the World. And the bodies are here named, not the perſons, becauſe perſecuting Tyrants (as we touched before) have no power over the ſoule, but only over the body; this they may torment, impriſon,<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.28.</note> kill: but thats all they can doe. Well, what of thoſe dead bodies, take them in any ſenſe? <hi>They ſhall lie in the ſtreet of the great Citie, which ſpiritually is called</hi> Sodome <hi>and</hi> Egypt, <hi>where alſo our Lord was crucified.</hi> What great City is this? Surely it can be no other, but the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Beaſt, together with the Suburbs. And the Suburbs are all thoſe Cities or States, which are either ſubject to, or confederate with the Head-Citie, which is <hi>Rome.</hi> We can not have a fitter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition hereof, then that which the Prelate of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury</hi> gives us in his reprinted Conference with the Jeſuite <hi>Fiſher.</hi> For there he ſaith; <hi>That the Church
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:157070:33"/> of</hi> Rome <hi>and the Church of</hi> England (as alſo all other Prelaticall or Hierarchicall Churches) <hi>are all one and the ſame Church; no doubt of that,</hi> as he ſaith, and as is noted before. This is his <hi>Catholike Church.</hi> And ſo this is that <hi>great City,</hi> which ſtands in oppoſition to the <hi>Holy Citie,</hi> and treads it under feet, as Verſe 2. For as Chriſts Church is called a <hi>Holy Citie,</hi> though it be diſperſed over the World: So Antichriſts Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue is here called a <hi>Great Citie,</hi> as comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in it all thoſe Cities, and States, which make up one body of the Beaſt. This <hi>great City is ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally called</hi> Sodome <hi>and</hi> Egypt: <hi>Sodome,</hi> for the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, voluptuouſneſſe, prophaneneſſe, pride, and other ſins of <hi>Sodome,</hi> raigning therein, and where they make open warre againſt all holineſſe, and all good Laws of GOD and Man. And ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is called <hi>Egypt,</hi> for its tyranny in oppreſſing and afflicting of Gods people with their intolerable burthens. And for this, they have their Task-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, to wit, the Prelates and their multitude of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, who force Gods people through their whole <hi>Egyptian</hi> Provinces to fill up their tale and task of bricks, in the ſtrict obſervation of all their Rites and Ceremonies, Conſtitutions, and Canons, the Spirituall burthens of their ſpirituall <hi>Egypt,</hi> and for default thereof in the leſt degree, or kind, the Taskmaſters beat and abuſe them, &amp; if they<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.15.</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, 'tis to no purpoſe, they can have no remedy. Thus not without cauſe is this <hi>Citie</hi> called not only <hi>Great,</hi> but <hi>ſpiritually</hi> Sodome <hi>and</hi> Egypt. So as in what Country ſoever in the World, this Beaſt ſets his paw, that is, where ever hee hath his Taskma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, the Prelates and their Officers (as where al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:157070:34"/> are they not? there is the Kingdome of the Beaſt, there be the Suburbs of this <hi>Great Citie.</hi> And whatever Countrey or State doth incorporate it ſelf into an union or confederation with this Papall Hierarchie, becomes thereby <hi>ipſo facto</hi> a member of this <hi>great Citie,</hi> which is <hi>ſpiritually called</hi> Sodome <hi>and</hi> Egypt. And this being ſo, tell me, ô <hi>England,</hi> art thou not become a member of this great body, of this <hi>Great Citie,</hi> of this <hi>ſpirituall Sodome,</hi> of this <hi>ſpirituall Egypt?</hi> For wherein doſt thou differ from <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe? Doth not thy great Arch-prelate who is as thine Oracle, profeſſe in thy name, and in Print, with an unbluſhing forehead, that <hi>England</hi> is of the<note n="u" place="margin">Conference Reprinted E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. Ded. pag. 16. And pag. 376. &amp; 338. &amp;c.</note> ſame Church, ſame faith, ſame Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion with <hi>Rome?</hi> And doth he not ſhrowd this his Book under the name of the higheſt Authoritie in <hi>England,</hi> as commanded by the King to be publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed? And haſt thou not ſet forth Edicts diſpenſing with the open profanation of the Sabbath by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh Sports, and others, prohibiting Miniſters to preach in the after-noons on Lords Days: as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring thy prophane Sports before the holy and divine Ordinance of Preaching, and ſo conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at leaſt the one halfe of the Lords Day to <hi>Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> or <hi>Belial?</hi> Art thou not then a part of that great Citie, which is ſpiritually called <hi>Sodome?</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, doſt thou not permit (if not command) thy Prelates, the <hi>Roman Pharoahs Taskmaſters</hi> to vex, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict, and grievouſly oppreſſe the people of God, with the intolerable burthens of their and thine endleſſe Ceremonies? And not<note n="x" place="margin">Theſe things were then in force when this Treatiſe was written.</note> content with the old, thou addeſt new burthens, as the <hi>Egyptians</hi> did
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:157070:34"/> in denying ſtraw, and thoſe moſt abominable, as thy Superſtitious, yea, Idolatrous Heatheniſh Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, with all their Idolatrous Altar-Service, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou art utterly falne from being a member of the <hi>Holy Citie,</hi> which thou <hi>treadeſt under thy feet,</hi> and even profeſſeſt thy ſelfe to be of that <hi>Great Citie,</hi> which for its inthralling and oppreſſing of Gods people, is <hi>ſpiritually called Egypt?</hi> O <hi>England, Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Repent hereof, caſt out thy curſed and cruell Taskmaſters, like as thy Neighbour <hi>Scotland</hi> hath done, &amp; ſo ſuffer thy people, Gods people, to ſerve their God as he hath commanded, and to enjoy their Chriſtian Libertie which Chriſt hath deerly purchaſed for them, and no longer to be under the Antichriſtian <hi>Babylonian</hi> yoake, and the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Taskmaſters.</p>
               <p>Thus we have ſeen, as it were in a Map, the large Territories, and bound leſſe bounds of this great City here mentioned, ſpiritually called <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Egypt;</hi> in the ſtreet whereof lie the <hi>dead bodies of Chriſts two witneſses:</hi> and where (as here is added) <hi>our Lord was crucified.</hi> Which is to be underſtood, not ſimply and perſonally of our Lords crucifying, but myſtically. For our Lord in Perſon was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and yet not within the Citie, but without the Gate. And yet Chriſt in his Perſon was crucified by the firſt <hi>Roman</hi> Beaſt, the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, whoſe Succeſſour both in his Seat, and in the Image of his Power and State, and in all his blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy perſecutions of the Saints, the Papall Beaſt now is; as alſo of the Scribes and Phariſees and High Prieſts, who put Chriſt to death, and ſo hee with them is guilty of his bloud: as <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.35, 36. &amp;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:157070:35"/> Verſe 31. But he is crucified myſtically in his my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall members, even in the open <hi>Streets</hi> of this <hi>Great Citie.</hi> Witneſſe all thoſe perſecutions and Martyrdomes, which the Beaſt in all Ages and Countries hath cauſed, wherein the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hath been crucified, to wit, in his Saints and Witneſſes. And what thinke you of thoſe Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, of whoſe crucifying on the Pillory in the open ſtreet, or rather ſpacious Palace-yard in the Citie of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> we have been all eye-witneſſes, and ſpectators? Was our Lord there, then, in them, on thoſe Pillories, crucified, or not? If he were, and that upon ſuch an eminent Theatre, and in the view of that Court, where they were ſo cenſured, the High Prieſts themſelves, with others of high note, beholding and pleaſing themſelves with ſuch a Tragedie of the Beaſts cunning contriving, and cruell execution: was not this, trow you, a part of that <hi>Great Citie,</hi> where our Lord hath been thus <hi>cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified?</hi> O <hi>England,</hi> bluſh, and be abaſhed, yea, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded in thy ſelf, at theſe things: return at length to a ſober minde, repent, and reforme thy ſelfe, leſt thou periſh with the Beaſt and his Kingdom, whoſe wofull ruine haſteneth on a pace; as Verſe 14.</p>
               <p>But now what becomes of theſe thus dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies? Surely they lie in the Street of the great Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie unburied. How long? Three dayes and an half. How ſo? The <hi>people, kindreds, tongues, and nations</hi> ſeeing them, wil not ſuffer them to be put in graves. Juſt ſo did the barbarous heathen with the Martyrs, not permitting their bodies to be buried, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as<note place="margin">Euſeb. Eccl. H iſt. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> reports. Thus our Antichriſtian hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then or <hi>Gentiles</hi> here, ſo called, Verſe 2. as before.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:157070:35"/> Now for dead bodies to lie in the open ſtreet unbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, three dayes and a halfe, is enough to make their ſmell odious and abominable in the noſthrils of all men. So as this appeares to be the meaning, theſe Witneſſes being ſlaine, or ſo, as is before ſaid, they are kept above ground to become an object of abomination to all that behold them; and by their long keeping, they are made ſo to ſtink, as men paſs by them ſtopping their Noſes, and will not, or doe not, or dare not come neere them. And who doth, or dare viſit the dead bodies of thoſe Witneſſes aforeſaid? But they are not in the <hi>Street.</hi> True: they are dragged, or drawn out of the Street, they doe ſo ſtinke in the noſthrils of the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and his <hi>kindred,</hi> and <hi>people.</hi> But yet they are above ground, they are not yet buried under the earth, though they lie buried within ſtrong walled vaults, that none can come any more at them, then at the dead bodies of thoſe that lie in their graves. But not lying in the ſtreet, and having lyen now above three dayes and a halfe, yea, ſome of them three yeeres and a halfe, and the leaſt and laſt is now going upon the laſt halfe yeere: how come they to bee reckoned here in the account, and numbred with the <hi>dead bodies</hi> of theſe <hi>two witneſses,</hi> lying <hi>three dayes and a halfe in the ſtreet of the great Citie?</hi> For this, we muſt take the ſenſe, and not the ſtrict Letter. The lying of dead bodies three days and a halfe in the open ſtreet, where all paſſengers are to paſſe, is to note unto us, that (as is before noted) they lie ſo long, till none can endure their ſmell, but of force they muſt bee removed out of the way. And is it not ſo done with theſe? Their ſmell grew ſo ſtrong,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:157070:36"/> that they were faine to remove them. Whither? Into their Graves? No, they are above ground ſtill. For it is added here, <hi>The people, and kindreds, and nations, and tongues, will not ſuffer their dead bodies to be put in graves.</hi> Who are theſe <hi>people, and kindreds, and tongues, and nations?</hi> Surely all thoſe of this <hi>great Citie,</hi> which is <hi>ſpiritually called</hi> Sodome <hi>and</hi> Egypt, ſuch as are the members of the <hi>Beaſt.</hi> For though ſometimes, theſe termes, as <hi>people, kindreds,</hi> &amp;c. are taken in the good part, for thoſe of Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as Chap. 7.9. &amp; 10.11. yet here they are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as Chap. 17.15. for thoſe of Antichriſts Kingdome. And for proofe hereof, they will not <hi>ſuffer the dead bodies of the two witneſses to be buried.</hi> As wee read of the Pope (as I remember <hi>Hildebrand</hi>) who after hee had by his Thunderbolt of Excommunication blaſted the Emperour, <hi>Henrie</hi> the Fourth, and driven him out of his Kingdome by his own Son, and he dying in that his exile, his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe would not ſuffer him to be buried, ſo as his dead body continued unburied for five yeers ſpace. So here, with the ſame ſpirit of Charity doe theſe his <hi>people,</hi> and <hi>kindreds,</hi> and <hi>tongues,</hi> and <hi>Nations,</hi> the whole body of that <hi>Beaſt,</hi> not <hi>ſuffer the dead bodies of theſe two witneſſes</hi> to enjoy the ordinary honour of Chriſtian buriall, which even the Law of Nature, and common humanity commands. The ſumme of it is, they will not allow them any benefit, nor any right, which by the Law of God, and the Law of Nature and Nations is due unto them in that caſe: So as being baniſhed in a remote Country in a cloſe impriſonment, living indeed, but as dead men (as before) they may there rot above ground, before
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:157070:36"/> either Wife, or children, or friend, or acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance ſhall be ſuffered to come at them to performe that laſt duty, which all are bound unto, the buriall of their dead. Thus if any ſhall deny this alſo, (concerning theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or dead bodies) to be a true <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Symptome of this Trumpets ſounding, which wee ought not to thinke gives an uncertain ſound: he may with as good reaſon deny the fulfilling of all Prophecies, even then, when their proper effects, being ſeene of all men, become to every mans reaſon and underſtanding, cleere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations thereof. Except wee are yet to looke for more monſtrous beaſtly cruelties under this Trumpet, which can hardly be imagined by any Creature.</p>
               <p>It followeth: <hi>And they that dwell upon the earth, ſhall rejoyce over them, and make merry, and ſhall ſend gifts one to another, becauſe theſe two Prophets tormented them that dwelt on the earth.</hi> Theſe Earth-dwellers are the ſame, with thoſe <hi>people,</hi> and <hi>kindreds,</hi> and <hi>tongues,</hi> and <hi>nations,</hi> thoſe of the Beaſts Kingdome, in the former Verſe. Theſe are ſaid <hi>to dwell on the earth,</hi> becauſe their Kingdome and happineſſe is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together earthly. They <hi>minde earthly things,</hi> and place their felicitie in them: contrary to Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, who living on earth, yet have their <hi>converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in heaven,</hi> and their <hi>treaſure in heaven,</hi> and their Country Heaven. So as to be ſaid to dwell on the earth, is oppoſed to thoſe, who are<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Gen.</hi> 47 9. <hi>Exod.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.54.</note> every where in Scripture called <hi>pilgrims and ſtrangers in the earth;</hi> and the earth it ſelfe called, not their habitation, but the land or houſe of their pilgrimage. Whereas on the contrary, to be ſaid <hi>to dwell on the earth,</hi> is uſually
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:157070:37"/> put in Scripture for all the wicked of the earth; as elſ-where in this Booke, Chap. 8.13. &amp; 13.12, 14. &amp; 17.8. Where we ſee, that theſe <hi>earth-dwellers</hi> are all thoſe people, over whom the Beaſt reigneth. And ſo, on theſe, all the plagues are powred: as Chap. 8.13. &amp; 12.12. &amp; 16.1. <hi>Luke</hi> 21.35. and in many other places. And in this Verſe it is twice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated. Thus we ſee who they be. Now what doe they further? Firſt, Theſe earth-dwellers rejoyce over the dead bodies of the witneſſes: Secondly, they make merry: Thirdly, they ſend gifts one to another, by way of congratulation. And the cauſe is added, becauſe theſe <hi>two witneſses tormented them that dwelt upon the earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, they <hi>rejoice over</hi> their dead bodies; as the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> did over <hi>Sampſon,</hi> when they had put out his eyes, they made ſport with him, as with a Fool in a Play. Hee whom they durſt not looke upon, when he had his eyes, and liberty, now they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult over him at their pleaſure. So theſe people of Antichriſt doe with the dead bodies of the two Witneſſes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sir</hi> Phil. Syd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys Arcadia.</note> as the cowardly Shepherd did in <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadia</hi> with the dead body of the Lion, he came and trampled upon him, and beat him with his ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hook, and ſpake big words unto him, and when hee had done, boaſted he had overcome the Lion. So theſe here do with theſe witneſſes: in the ſeventh Verſe the Beaſt overcomes them: and here his brood triumphs over them, who living were a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to the beaſt, and all his crew.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>they make merry.</hi> The Father in the Goſpel when he had received his loſt Son, is ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to make merry; the ſame word is uſed
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:157070:37"/> here, upon the ſlaying of theſe witneſſes, as a fat Calfe, to feaſt withall. And ſuch a kind of mirth is here implyed, as is uſed at feaſting. As in <hi>Amos</hi> (Chap. 2.8.) <hi>They drinke the wine of the condemned in the houſe of their God;</hi> to wit, of thoſe whom them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have unjuſtly condemned. So theſe. Perhaps they have their Minſtrels too, as Fidlers and Pipers, &amp; dance about the May-pole, &amp; that on the <hi>Sabbath day,</hi> in deſpight of theſe Witneſſes, who while they lived ſpake and wrote againſt theſe inhabitants of the ſpirituall <hi>Sodome.</hi> But let their mirth be what it will: in the third place, <hi>they ſend gifts one to another.</hi> They doe not ſend gifts to the poore, of whom they can receive none again: but one to another, by way of retaliation or congratulation: this is their charitie, as if they would now celebrate the fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of theſe dead witneſſes, would they but ſuffer their dead bodies to be buried.</p>
               <p>But what's the matter they are ſo jocund and fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick? Even this, becauſe theſe two <hi>Prophets had tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented them that dwell on the earth.</hi> It ſeemes they were ſuch tormenters of theſe Earth-dwellers, as the Prophet<note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>Kings</hi> 22.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Michaiah</hi> was of <hi>Ahab;</hi> who therefore hated him, and could not indure him, becauſe (ſaith he) <hi>be never prophecieth good to me but evil.</hi> So theſe two Prophets, they tormented all thoſe of the Beaſts Kingdome by prophecying of judgements and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments that ſhould fall upon them from God for all their idolatries, ſuperſtitions, humane inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the Service they pretend to God, for all their abominable infidelitie in their <hi>Altars,</hi> and Altar-worſhip, for their open and avowed prophanation of the Sabbath, for their ſtopping of the mouthes
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:157070:38"/> of Gods painfull Miniſters, for oppreſſing and ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the Doctrines of the Goſpel, and of the Grace of God, for overturning all true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, for perſecuting of all true godlineſſe in Miniſters and people, for their favouring of drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, adulterers, ſwearers, Sabbath-breakers, and all manner of prophaneſſe in their Courts, with other the like things, as tedious to rehearſe, as to them to heare. Thus theſe <hi>Prophets tormented them.</hi> Now I pray you what torments ſhall ſuch finde in Hell for their living in all kinde of ſin, when they find Gods Word it ſelf to be a tormentor of them, in reproving their ſins, and moving them to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance? Is it a marvaile then, that all the woes in this Book fall upon theſe dwellers on the earth? They doe ſo dwell on the earth, that they are glued unto it, ſo as they will not upon any termes, no not to get Heaven, and ſo eſcape Hell, part with the love of it, and with the luſts of it. And therefore they hold none their greater enemies, then Gods Prophets, that tell them their own. And of other prophane Worldlings, none hate Gods Prophets more, than the Beaſt, and his Hierarchie. For their Kingdome being altogether <hi>earthly,</hi> and <hi>ſenſuall,</hi> (I might adde alſo the Apoſtles third word, which he applyes to the wiſdome that is from beneath, from the bottomleſſe pit, and that is,<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iam.</hi> 3.15.</note> Devilliſh) they cannot endure Chriſts Kingdome, which is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Spirituall, nor the Heralds thereof, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clame war againſt the Beaſt, and his Armies, for his notorious hypocriſie, who under the titles of Holineſſe, and Spirituall, and the like, advance their earthly Kingdome both above and againſt Chriſts Kingdome.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:157070:38"/>
               <p>It followeth: Verſe 11. <hi>And after three dayes and a halfe, the ſpirit of life from God entred into them, and they ſtood upon their feet, and great feare fell upon them which ſaw them.</hi> Wee ſhewed before what is meant by the three days and a halfe, namely, the time, in which the Beaſt and his people doe expoſe theſe witneſſes to deriſion, denying them even that common humanity, which the very Heathen freely afford to all, as buriall of the dead. And although the time of their ſuffering may bee much longer then three days and a halfe, yea, three yeeres and a halfe, yet it is reckoned here but three dayes and a halfe, both becauſe the Beaſts crueltie is ſo great, that he takes no more compaſsion or conſideration of the time of their ſuffering, though long and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, then as if it were but three dayes and a half: and ſecondly, becauſe ſuch is the patience and ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critie of theſe Witneſſes in ſuffering for the Name of Chriſt, and for the love of the Truth, that the time, though long, and the afflictions they indure, though very grievous, yet it ſeemes to them but<note n="b" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4 17.</note> light, and momentany, and as it were but of three dayes and a halfes continuance, in compariſon: and Thirdly, it is expreſſed here by three dayes and a halfe, becauſe the Lord himſelfe will ſhorten the time, and haſten the deliverance in due time, in due time, I ſay, becauſe it is a certaine time, determined and prefixed of God; as three dayes and a halfe; and becauſe but as three dayes and a halfe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is a very ſhort time, as will appeare more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when the deliverance commeth. But laſtly, by three dayes and a halfe, wee may underſtand three yeeres and a half, as in <hi>Daniel</hi> 7.25. by a time, times,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:157070:39"/> and part or halfe a time, three yeeres and part of another. As <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.14. And why ſhould I here conceale that ſpeech which I uſed to ſome Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters at <hi>Coventry</hi> in my paſſage to <hi>Lancaſter</hi> Caſtle, who being ſad at my departure, I ſaid unto them, Come, be not ſad, for three yeers and a half hence wee ſhall meet again, and be merry. And truly <hi>(ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit invidia verbo)</hi> reckoning from the fourteenth of <hi>June</hi> 1637, whereon we were cenſured in the Star-Chamber to perpetuall impriſonment, it was juſt three yeeres and a halfe when wee returned from exile, even in the laſt moneth of the three yeers and a halfe, my ſelfe being ſent for the very firſt day of that moneth.</p>
               <p>Well, when this time, appointed of God, is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired, what then? Then, <hi>after three dayes and a half, the ſpirit of life from God ſhall enter into them: and they ſhall ſtand upon their feet, and great feare ſhall fall upon the beholders.</hi> All this ſheweth unto us thus much, that God ſhall miraculouſly reſtore and deliver his witneſſes, even as the reſtoring of the dead to life again, to the aſtoniſhment and terrour of all their enemies, who ſhall behold them. But now a little more, particularly to cleere the words: we ſhewed before how the Lord's witneſſes may be ſlain two wayes, either corporally, in ſeparating their ſouls from their bodies, or myſtically, and in a ſimilitude or parable, in a ſeparation of their life from the world, that is from all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>merce &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion with the world, ſo as their life is made no better, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worſe then death. Now for them that are ſlain after the firſt manner, we are not to expect, that God wil according to the Letter rayſe them up from the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:157070:39"/> dead, as here, after three days and a halfe. And for them that are ſlain after the ſecond manner here ſpecified, though God ſhould not deliver and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore them from that their civill death, (though he be able to do it, and will doe it, if he have ſo deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined) unto their libertie, and communion with humane ſocietie, as formerly: Yet this we are ſure of, as Gods Word here muſt needs be true, that of the very duſt and aſhes of his dead witneſſes under this Trumpet (in what manner ſo ever dead) hee will raiſe up again to life, and that in the time of this Trumpet, either thoſe very witneſſes in their own perſons, or elſe in the Spirit of theſe hee will raiſe up other witneſſes, and ſuch, as if they were thoſe very witneſſes formerly ſlain. Thus wee read of <hi>Elias,</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.5, 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>I will ſend you</hi> Elias <hi>the Prophet, before the comming of the great and dreadfull day of the Lord, and he ſhall turn the heart of the Fathers to the children, &amp;c.</hi> Now this <hi>Elias</hi> was meant of <hi>John the Baptiſt,</hi> that <hi>morning Star,</hi> that uſhered in the<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſse,</hi> that was to prepare the way before him.<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 1.17.</note> 
                  <hi>He</hi> (ſaith the Angell to <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariah) ſhall goe before him in the Spirit and power of</hi> Elias, <hi>to turn the heart of the Fathers to the Children, &amp;c.</hi> Whence it is plaine and cleere, that <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi> was that <hi>Elias</hi> there prophecied of; and he is called <hi>Elias,</hi> becauſe hee came <hi>in the ſpirit and power of Elias.</hi> And therefore Chriſt faith to his Diſciples, when they objected, that <hi>Elias</hi> muſt firſt come:<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 17.11</note> 
                  <hi>I tell you</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that</hi> Elias <hi>is come already,</hi> &amp;c. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they underſtood, that hee ſpake unto them of <hi>John the Baptiſt.</hi> And <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.14. Speaking of <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>This is</hi> Elias, <hi>which was to come.</hi>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:157070:40"/> Thus wee ſee, how the Prophet <hi>Elias,</hi> being dead and buried many hundred yeers before, yet was as it were raiſed up from the dead, to be Chriſts har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binger. But how? Not in his perſon, but in his <hi>ſpirit</hi> and <hi>power.</hi> So as <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> comming in the <hi>ſpirit and power of</hi> Elias, is called <hi>Elias,</hi> and in him the Prophecie is fulfilled, that <hi>Elias ſhould come,</hi> and now in <hi>Iohn</hi> he was already come. Now according to this ſenſe, wee may ſafely interpret this Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie alſo in this place: <hi>After three dayes and a halfe, the ſpirit of life from God, ſhall enter into them</hi> (to wit, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the two ſlain witneſſes) <hi>and they ſhall ſtand upon their feet, &amp;c:</hi> that is, after a ſhort, but ſet time with God, <hi>the ſpirit of life from God ſhall rayſe up his former witneſſes,</hi> that were ſlain, though not in their owne perſons, yet in other witneſſes that ſhall ſucceed them, who ſhall be indued with the ſame <hi>ſpirit and power,</hi> which they had beene indued with all. And this is that <hi>ſpirit of life from God,</hi> which <hi>entring into his ſervants,</hi> raiſeth them up to be lively witneſſes of his truth, full of vigour, ſtrength, courage, zeale, conſtancie,<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.11.</note> not loving their lives unto the death, but as it is ſaid of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> ſuch as had<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 15.26.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>abandoned,</hi> or <hi>given up for loſt</hi> their lives for the Name of Chriſt. So that, as the ſame ſpirit of life from God entring into <hi>Iohn the Baptiſt,</hi> made him to be called that <hi>Elias,</hi> who had been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with the ſame <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and was foretold to come againe, which was fulfilled in the <hi>Baptiſt:</hi> So here, the ſame <hi>ſpirit of life from God</hi> (nor is it ſaid to bee their own ſpirit) which the ſlain witneſſes had, now entring into other witneſſes ſucceeding them, they by the ſame reaſon may be called thoſe very wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:157070:40"/> as being now by the Almighty power of GOD raiſed from the dead, as <hi>Iohn the Baptiſt</hi> was called that <hi>Elias,</hi> becauſe hee came in the <hi>ſpirit and power of Elias.</hi> And in this reſpect, ſeeing the raiſing and reſtoring of theſe two witneſſes, is perhaps not perſonall, but ſpiritual, it is not neceſſary, that we tie or reſtrain the ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding witneſſes ſtrictly to the number of two only. For as it was ſaid of old, <hi>Sanguis Martyrum ſemen Eccleſiae, The bloud of the Martyrs is the ſeed of the Church:</hi> and as one ſeed or grain ſowne, and dying, brings forth much fruit (as<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.24.</note> Chriſt ſaith) ſo as one corne brings forth the increaſe of a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and ſome of a thouſand, as in ſome Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, as of <hi>Virginia:</hi> So theſe two witneſſes may in the multiplication of their ſpirit and power, and of that ſpirit of life from God, bring forth an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant harveſt, even great plenty of more wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, that ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll ſtand up for that Truth, for the which theſe two were ſlaine. What ſhall wee ſay of thoſe many witneſſes, whom the Lord lately raiſed up in <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſtanding up upon their feet to mayntain their Chriſtian Liberty againſt Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian bondage, and to vindicate Chriſts Scepter and Government over his Church there out of the tyrannicall hands of that proud uſurping <hi>Beaſt</hi> out of the <hi>bottomleſſe pit,</hi> who by his <hi>Egyptian</hi> Taskma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters the Prelates ſo oppreſſed Gods people, as they were made weary of their lives? And when were theſe witneſſes raiſed up? Surely, not much after three dayes and a halfe, that the two witneſſes were ſlaine, thoſe (I meane) who ſuffered worſe then
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:157070:41"/> death, for bearing witneſſe againſt the Tyranny of the Romiſh Beaſt, and his cruell Taskmaſters. And what other ſpirit, but that <hi>ſpirit of life from God,</hi> could raiſe up ſo many witneſſes, ſo unanimouſly, and with ſuch a wonderfull wiſdome, diſcretion, judgement, zeal, and courage, to ſtand up in defence of Chriſts Kingdome againſt Antichriſts Tyranny? Yea, and what other ſpirit and power, but that of God, could move the heart of his anointed Vicegerent, to aſſent to his peoples juſt and religious plea, to have Chriſt alone to raigne over his peoples ſoules and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, which is his peculiar and incommunicable Prerogative. Nor could the King either have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced higher his own Royall honour, or more ſurely have eſtabliſhed his owne Throne in the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and faſtening of his Subjects hearts and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in all love and loyalty unto him, then by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Chriſt his due honour, who hath ſaid,<note n="k" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30.</note> 
                  <hi>Thoſe that honour me, I will honour: and they that deſpiſe mee, ſhall be lightly eſteemed.</hi> Now bleſſed bee our God for evermore for this his great and glorious worke: and hee ever bleſſe his King, that as hee hath made him a mighty inſtrument thereof; ſo hee would ſtrengthen him to the finiſhing of that work, which yet remaynes to be done in the purgation and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of his other Kingdomes, that ſo hee may prove the moſt glorious Prince that ever raigned in the Chriſtian World.</p>
               <p>And it is ſaid here, <hi>And great feare fell upon them which ſaw them.</hi> That is, when they on the Beaſts ſide ſaw thoſe witneſſes (whom the Beaſt had cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly ſlaine, and whoſe dead bodies they had barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly uſed, not ſuffering them to have common
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:157070:41"/> buriall, but inſulted, and triumphed over them) now to be as it were revived and raiſed from the dead againe, when they behold ſuch a wonderfull increaſe to come of their bloud ſo cruelly ſhed, ſuch a <hi>ſpirit of life from God</hi> ſo to poſſeſſe many other witneſſes, as thoſe ſlain ſeem<floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="note">
                     <body>
                        <p>Here let the Reader ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that this Treatiſe was written before his returne from baniſhment, and ſo towards <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> on that Saturday, the ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie whereof was ſo conſpicuous and glorious, as it doth, without any other application, even na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally apply it ſelf, as if it were the moſt proper fulfilling of this Prophecie, if either wee conſider the manner of that return, or the effect it wrought in the adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries thereof, which cauſed in them extreame indignation and rage, even unto gnawing of their tongues, and gnaſhing of their teeth. And yet feare ſo poſſeſſed them, that all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>heir power and policie could not help.</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText> now to live againe in them: they are ſtruck with terrour, they are ſurprized with feare. For whereas they fondly imagined, that the ſlaying, or cruell handling of two or three prime witneſſes, making them ſure, as dead men, would ſo have queld all the reſt, that not one durſt ever after peepe: contrary to their expectation they ſee a genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of witneſſes to riſe up after them, and ſo to affright their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as if they ſaw an apparition of the Ghoſts of the former witneſſes returned from the dead. And if a man did now but feele the pulſe of thoſe Prelates in <hi>England,</hi> who have ſeene their brethren Prelates, late of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> caſt out of Church and Countrey, and utterly caſhiered, without all hope of reſtitution: ſhould he not (trow you) find the ſpirit of trepidation leap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and panting as it were for life, as if their owne turne ſhould be next? But it followeth:</p>
               <p>Verſe 12. <hi>And they heard a great voice from heaven, ſaying unto them, Come up hither. And they aſcended up to heaven in a cloud, and their enemies beheld them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They</hi> (that is, the two witneſſes thus raiſed and reſtored to life, as before) <hi>heard a great voice from
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:157070:42"/> heaven.</hi> Here Chriſt, either by an extraordinary voice inwardly calling, or by the ordinary voice of his word outwardly, cals his ſervants to take San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, as in heaven. Now heaven, here may bee taken for the Church of God hereupon earth. So it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> often taken in this Booke. As in this Chapter, Verſe 19. So Chap. 12.1. the woman there in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is the Church Militant here on earth, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth plainly in the whole Chapter, as Verſe 3. &amp; 7. &amp; 8. &amp; Chap. 13.6. and in other places. Now the Church of God here on earth is compared unto, and called Heaven, as in many other reſpects, ſo ſpecially in this, becauſe it is holy and pure, being purged, both for Doctrine, and Diſcipline, from all damnable Hereſies and errours in faith, and from the vain Inventions and Traditions of men in the worſhip of God,<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Revel.</hi> 14.4.</note> following the Lambe whither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he goeth, that is, in all things obeying Chriſt, and obſerving his Ordinances, and ſubjecting their ſouls and conſciences to none other King, but only Chriſt.</p>
               <p>They from this Heaven, heare a great voice: this is Chriſts voice in his word, calling his witneſſes from having any more to doe with the Beaſt, and his brood, having ſealed this their teſtimony with their bloud, which the Beaſt hath ſucked and drunk up. So as hee now being found to be incorrigible, and incurable, ſo as hee grows worſe and worſe, is to be utterly abandoned. As the Lord ſaith in <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 51.6.45</note> 
                  <hi>Flee out of the midſt of</hi> Babylon, <hi>and deliver every man his ſoule: be not cut off in her iniquitie: for this is the time of the Lords vengeance, he will render unto her a recompence.</hi> And the reaſon of Gods peoples thus
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:157070:42"/> abandoning of <hi>Babylon,</hi> is rendred, Verſe 9.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 9.</note> 
                  <hi>We would have healed</hi> Babylon, <hi>but ſhee is not healed: forſake her, and let us goe every one into his owne Countrey: for her judgement reacheth up to heaven, and is lifted up even to the skies.</hi> And the like warning God gives to his people (<hi>Revel.</hi> 18.4.) concerning the <hi>ſpirituall Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> where <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>I heard another voice from heaven, ſaying, Come out of her my people, that ye be not partakers of her ſins, and that ye receive not of her plagues: for her ſins have reached unto heaven, and God hath remembred her iniquities.</hi> So here, the witneſſes heare <hi>a great voice from heaven,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Come up hither;</hi> as much to ſay, as, <hi>Have no more to doe with</hi> Babylon, <hi>nor with the Beaſt and his members, who will heare no reaſon, but have now filled up the meaſure of their cruelty, not only to you, but to all my witneſſes that went before you, ſo as now there is no more hope of them,</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 17. See alſo 2 <hi>Chron</hi> 36.16.</note> 
                  <hi>no remedie for them, being like thoſe incorrigible and obſtinate revolted Tribes of Iſrael, or like the</hi> Jews, <hi>that perſecuted my Apoſtles, and</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 13.46.</note> 
                  <hi>drove them away to the</hi> Gentiles: <hi>therefore come out from among them, admoniſh them no more, but come up hither, keepe you cloſe to my Church, which I have altogether purged and purified from the dregs of</hi> Babylon, <hi>and there only hold your communion. Come up hither.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And</hi> (as it followeth) <hi>they aſcended up to heaven in a cloud, and their enemies beheld them.</hi> Wee read, that <hi>Elias</hi> was carried up to heaven in a <hi>fiery Chariot.</hi> And <hi>Chriſt</hi> aſcended up to Heaven in a <hi>cloud.</hi> Here theſe <hi>witneſſes</hi> aſcend up to <hi>heaven</hi> in a <hi>cloud.</hi> But to Heaven (as before is ſhewed) namely, from their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to take Sanctuary as in the Church of God here on earth; it being compared to a high and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mountain, to which we muſt aſcend. So as this
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:157070:43"/> aſcending in a cloud, and that in the enemies view, ſets forth the admirable providence of God, who will miraculouſly make his Church a ſure and ſafe Sanctuary (as Heaven) to his perſecuted ones under this <hi>Trumpet,</hi> from the power and fury of their <hi>ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies;</hi> who may behold them afarre off, but are not able any more to touch them, for they are now out of their reach, as being in Heaven. For in this <hi>Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet,</hi> God is preparing a way to the ſeventh, and laſt <hi>Trumpet,</hi> wherein hee will take full vengeance upon <hi>Babylon.</hi> And therefore before the ſtorme come, God hath a <hi>hiding place,</hi> to ſecure his. As hee ſaith in <hi>Eſay,</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 4.5, 6.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord will create upon every dwelling place of Mount</hi> Sion, <hi>and upon her aſsemblies, a Cloud and Smoake by day, and the ſhining of a flaming fire by night; for upon all the glory ſhall be a defence. And there ſhall be a Tabernacle for a ſhadow in the day time from the heat, and for a place of refuge, and for a covert from ſtorme, and from rain.</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.</note> Thus the Lord did, when he was about to deſtroy the firſt-born of <hi>Egypt;</hi> he ſhut up his people in their houſes, ſprinkling them with the bloud of the Paſchall Lambe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.</note> that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venger ſhould not touch them. And when the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian</hi> hoſt purſued them as farre as the Red Sea, the Lord ſeparated them by the pillar of a Cloud by day, and of fire by night, untill hee had over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed the Hoaſt in the Sea. And when he was about to deſtroy <hi>Sodome,</hi> he firſt ſeparates <hi>Lot</hi> from among them. So before hee deſtroy <hi>Babylon,</hi> hee<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> cals his people out of her, and then quickly after in the ſame Chapter follows her ruine, and deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. So here, the Lord calling his witneſſes away, and they aſcending up to their Sanctuary in a cloud
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:157070:43"/> in the fight of their enemies, it is a ſure and certain ſigne, and immediate forerunner of the deſtruction of this <hi>Babylon,</hi> that <hi>great Citie,</hi> which is <hi>ſpiritually called</hi> Sodome <hi>and</hi> Egypt. And it is very remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that before the deſtruction of all theſe three, <hi>Sodome, Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Babylon,</hi> the Lord doth imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly before ſeparate his people, and provide a San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary for them. Yea, not long before the utter and finall<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioſephus,</hi> Of the wars of the <hi>Iews.</hi>
                  </note> deſtruction of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> (which was once Gods true Church, but now was become the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue of Murtherers, and Perſecutors of Chriſt, and his Saints) there was a voice heard in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as from Heaven, <hi>Migremus hinc, Let us depart hence:</hi> whereby Gods ſmall remnant yet there, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing warned, preſently fled to <hi>Pella,</hi> a Coaſt-Citie in <hi>Iudea,</hi> and not long after followed the ſacking and burning of the Citie and Temple, with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants therein. Thus by theſe many famous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples we may cleerly ſee what God is now about in this Trumpet to doe, when he cals away his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Sodome,</hi> and the Synagogue of Antichriſt, and puts them in a ſafe Sanctuary, even becauſe he will ſpeedily bring de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction upon thoſe his enemies.</p>
               <p>It followeth, Verſe 13.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 13.</note> 
                  <hi>And the ſame houre was there a great Earthquake, and the tenth part of the Citie fell, and in the Earthquake were ſlaine of men ſeven thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, and the remnant were affrighted, and gave glory to the God of Heaven.</hi> See here, no ſooner have the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes taken Sanctuary, but by and by, even the ſame houre, there is <hi>a great Earthquake.</hi> Now though there have been in the World (and ſtill fall out) ſundry great Earthquakes in diverſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:157070:44"/> as in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and other places: yet in this place, under this <hi>Trumpet,</hi> this <hi>great Earthquake</hi> here is not to be taken literally, no more then <hi>heaven</hi> in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Verſe, for the place of the higheſt <hi>heaven.</hi> But the <hi>great Earthquake</hi> here is to be underſtood of the great and terrible ſhaking of the Kingdomes of the earth under the ſound of this <hi>Trumpet,</hi> as namely by great Commotions, Wars, and the like, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in Chriſtendome, throughout the Kingdome of the Beaſt. And when was Chriſtendome ever more embroyled in wars, then at this day? But here it is ſaid, that <hi>the tenth part of the Citie fell.</hi> This is joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the former, as an effect of this <hi>great Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake.</hi> Firſt, what is meant by the Citie here? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that great City, mentioned, V. 8. Which we have before deſcribed; even the Kingdom of the Beaſt. And ſtill all the plagues and woes, which both the Trumpets ſound forth, and the ſeven Vialls powre out, fall upon the Beaſt, and his Kingdome. So as there is no queſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, but this Citie here is that <hi>great Citie,</hi> Antichriſts large Kingdome. And what is meant by the tenth part of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? For reſolution hereof, wee read, that the<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 17.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Beaſt</hi> with <hi>ſeven heads</hi> hath <hi>ten hornes.</hi> And theſe<note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 12.</note> 
                  <hi>ten hornes</hi> are ſaid to be <hi>ten Kings.</hi> Theſe ten Kings are ſaid to be the <hi>ten hornes,</hi> becauſe they are the ſtrength of the Beaſt. And the <hi>ten Kings</hi> have their ten Kingdomes, which make up the Beaſts Kingdome, or his <hi>great Citie.</hi> Now what Kingdoms are thoſe, which are ſaid to be of this great body of this <hi>great Citie?</hi> Surely thoſe, which doe admit, and maintaine the Papall power. The Papall power is maintained by Civill States or Kingdomes two
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:157070:44"/> ways. Either when they directly and profeſſedly ſubject their Thrones and Crowns to the Pope, as to the Head of the Church, by vertue of which title he arrogates to himſelfe a Supreame power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Kings</hi> and Princes (which is to<note n="y" place="margin">2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.4.</note> exalt himſelfe <hi>above all that is called God</hi>) to depoſe, and diſpoſe at his pleaſure: or when they doe it only implicitly, or by ſome privy compact or league, or otherwiſe, by admitting in their Kingdomes the Popes Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchie (for the Hierarchie is meerly Papall, where ever it be erected) which Hierarchie conſiſting in the Prelates, as it is in it ſelfe a proper and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall member and prop of his Kingdome: So it is a mighty and maine inſtrument of bringing into Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to the Pope thoſe Kingdomes and people, wherein, and over whom they are exalted in their Epiſcopall Thrones, as they call them. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in a Civill Kingdome or State, where the Goſpel is profeſſed, &amp; the Popes Supremacy diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and the juriſdiction of Prelates by Law limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as being of humane inſtitution meerly, and not by divine authoritie, Prelats, when they are pinch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and held cloſe to it, may perhaps pull in their hornes, and arrogate no more unto themſelves, then the Laws of the Land, or pleaſure of the Prince do allow unto them: yet when their inbred pride and ambition (an inſeparable accident, or rather eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall qualitie of a Prelate) findes opportunitie, meeting with a <hi>debonaire</hi> and benigne Prince, into whoſe gentle breſt they can eaſily inſinuate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and by their dexteritie in the art of flattery, and nimbleneſſe of tongue and wit, perſwade and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:157070:45"/> work upon his ſweet nature ſo, as to draw it to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a reverend opinion of their counterfeit ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which they ſet out in a goodly garbe of their ſuperſtitious guiſes in their wil-worſhip, and by this means to a credulitie in believing all to be Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, which they ſay: as for the purpoſe, that they are the true Church; that they have a power to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain Ceremonies in the Church: that Chriſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained them to be his<note n="x" place="margin">Reprinted Conference, <hi>p.</hi> 200. 210. 211</note> Vice-roys: that they are the only Judges in controverſies of faith: that Princes muſt leave all government of the Church to them, as the ſole Fathers thereof: and ſuch like Prelaticall Principles, which are not to be found in <hi>rerum natura,</hi> as they beg: when once they have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained credit to theſe things, how doe they then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtir themſelves, eſpecially where a pragmaticall pate, and the Metropolitan Chaire meet together? Then, what Laws of the Kingdom ſhal bind them? Who ſhall dare to controule them? If Parliaments (whoſe Laws they break as ſtraws) offer to meddle with them, preſently they muſt be diſſolved, and with their good will there ſhall never be Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment more. And in fine, they grow to that heighth of inſolencie, that their meere luſt muſt be a Law, as all their practices proclame.<note place="margin">Reprinted Conference, <hi>p.</hi> 338. 376. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> Nor doe their practices only overthrow all true religion, but they come to make open profeſſion, that the religion and faith of Prelaticall Proteſtant Churches, and by name of that of <hi>England,</hi> is one and the ſame with that of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Church of <hi>England</hi> one and the ſame with that of <hi>Rome,</hi> with many ſuch like bold aſſertions, all which tend to make a recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:157070:45"/> and a re-union with <hi>Rome,</hi> to whom al Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laticall Churches in the World (and they allow no other Churches for true, but only the Prelaticall) doe make up one intire Catholike Church. Now all theſe being ſummed up together, what doe they amount unto, but this, that all Prelaticall Churches hold with <hi>Rome,</hi> as members of the ſame Catholike body, and the Pope being the Head of this body, at leaſt<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 183. 184.</note> 
                  <hi>ordine primus,</hi> which the Prelate ſaith is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary: <hi>Ergo,</hi> all Prelaticall Churches are mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of that Church, whereof the Pope is the Head, or at leaſt <hi>ordine primus,</hi> and conſequently all Civill Kingdomes and States, where the Prelacie or Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchie hath got any footing, and much more where it hath gotten head, muſt bee a member thereof. Now this being ſo (as ſo it is) the way is now made plaine, to come to know what is meant by the fall of the tenth part of the Citie. What is it, but the fall of one of the ten Kingdomes from the Pope, which are the ten horns of his Hierarchie, in the time of this ſixt Trumpet? But where ſhall we find ſuch a Kingdome, as was one of the ten horns of the Beaſt, and now broken off and falne from that great head? Where? What ſay you to the Church of <hi>Scotland?</hi> Had not the Prelates there throwne down to the ground Chriſts throne, and conſequently with it, the Kings Throne, his Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent, and in ſtead thereof mounted aloft the Throne and Kingdome of the Beaſt, with their Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall and lawleſſe Government? But now we ſee the Beaſts Throne in that Kingdome diſmoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. For now the Prelats with their Hierarchie are there caſhiered. And thus the <hi>tenth part of the Citie
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:157070:46"/> is falne.</hi> But what was the occaſion of this great fall? Surely, <hi>Pride will have a fall.</hi> The Prelats intolerable inſolencie and unſufferable Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie did cauſe it. Which makes mee remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber a notable ſaying, or I may call it rather a prophecie, of a<note n="b" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Throg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morton.</hi>
                  </note> godly Miniſter late of <hi>London. As</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>nothing cures the biting of the Scorpion, but the oile of the Scorpion: So nothing will cure Popery, but Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery.</hi> And this was here verified. What cured the Popery, which the Prelacie had brought and ſet up in <hi>Scotland,</hi> but their extream haſte, and mad zeale to finiſh the building up of <hi>Rome</hi> in one day? To this purpoſe I remember an other uſuall ſaying of another Miniſter alſo late of <hi>London,</hi> who when any ſpake of a bad, or mad Prelate, hee would ſtill ſay, <hi>The worſe, the better, and the better the worſe.</hi> His meaning was, that the worſe the Biſhops grew, and the more inſolent, and tyrannicall, the more they did haſten the fall of their proud Hierarchie. As Chriſt ſaid to the <hi>Phariſees, Fill yee up the meaſure of your Fathers.</hi> As the people of God could not come to their promiſed inheritance, till the<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 15 16.</note> 
                  <hi>ſins of the</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monites <hi>were growne to their full.</hi> And the<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Revel.</hi> 14.18, 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Angell thruſt not his ſickle into the earth, to gather the Vine thereof, to caſt it into the great Winepreſse of the wrath of God, till the cluſters were ripe.</hi> And now in <hi>Scotland</hi> the clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.</note> 
                  <hi>Vine of Sodome</hi> were growne ripe, and ſo they are cut down. And thus <hi>the tenth part of the Citie is falne,</hi> thus the <hi>Beaſt</hi> hath loſt one of his ten horns. And to conclude this, The immediate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall cauſe of this fall, was the <hi>Earthquake.</hi> And an <hi>Earthquake</hi> (wee know) is the immediate worke of God alone. So as this ſheweth unto us,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:157070:46"/> that it was Gods owne hand and work principally, that did overthrow this <hi>tenth part of the Citie,</hi> and Kingdome of the Beaſt. For it was a building too deep-founded in the earth, for mans either power to overturn it, or policie to undermine it. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let all the glory be given to God alone.</p>
               <p>It followeth: <hi>And in the Earthquake were ſlain of men ſeven thouſand.</hi> We ſhewed before, that an <hi>Earthquake</hi> may be taken tropically for ſome civil Commotion in a State, as of late in the ſtate of <hi>Scotland,</hi> when all ſtood up as one intire body to vindicate their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty from the Beaſts Tyranny, which the Prelates did exerciſe upon the people; ſo as the iſſue here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of proved to be the fall of the <hi>tenth part of the Citie,</hi> or Kingdome of the Beaſt, in <hi>Scotlands</hi> falling quite off from the Papall Hierarchie. Now theſe words <hi>[And in the Earthquake were ſlaine of men ſeven thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand]</hi> have reference to the ſame Earthquake<note n="h" place="margin">Objection.</note>. But no men were ſlaine in that <hi>Scotland</hi> Earthquake: and here ſeven thouſand men are ſaid to be ſlaine. 'Tis true. But as the Earthquake is taken tropically, ſo alſo the ſlaying here; as we ſpake before of a ſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>two witneſses,</hi> in a civill reſpect, or in a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure: So here, by ſlaying, we underſtand a ceaſing of a thing to be that, which it was before. As a man is ſaid to be<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.2.</note> 
                  <hi>dead to ſin,</hi> becauſe hee no longer lives the life of ſin. Now for the <hi>ſeven thouſand</hi> here <hi>ſlain in the Earthquake, ſeven,</hi> we know, is a perfect num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and often comprehends a whole ſociety, or all of ſuch a Profeſsion, or qualitie, in the ſame place, or Countrey. As the<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.</note> ſeven Churches, the ſeven Stars, the ſeven Candleſticks, comprehending all the Churches and Miniſters in <hi>Aſia</hi> the leſſe. So
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:157070:47"/>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 19.18.</note> ſeven thouſand men were reſerved of God in <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> even all thoſe who did not bow to <hi>Baal.</hi> And ſo here ſeven thouſand may comprehend all thoſe, who in the ſaid <hi>Earthquake</hi> in <hi>Scotland</hi> were <hi>ſlaine,</hi> that is, were caſt out of their places, and ſo ceaſed to bee that, which they were before, and thoſe were the Prelates, with all their Officers, and train, even the whole Hierarchie. And the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the text, is not altogether to be ſlighted; for it ſignifieth not only names, but men of fame and<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 6 4.</note> renowne, ſuch as were the Giants and Tyrants of old, and thoſe<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Babel</hi>-builders, who would get them a Name by building that Towre. And ſuch are thoſe men we ſpeak of, theſe Giants, Tyrants, <hi>Babel</hi>-builders, they are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, men of Renown, terrible men, yea, not only the Lord-prelates themſelves, but their whole retinue, for not a Purſuivant and Apparitor, and the leaſt Boy in their Kitchin, but he is a mickle man. Well, all theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, even ſeven thouſand, the whole generation of them in <hi>Scotland</hi> is ſlaine in that Earthquake, that is, utterly caſt out as dead men. For ſtill (I ſay) theſe plagues fall only on them that have the Beaſts marke, or the number of his Name, as the Prelats, and their followers. And if any here ſtand ſtrictly upon the juſt Number of ſeven thouſand, I anſwer, whether there were more of them, or whether fewer, the Number of ſeven thouſand being a perfect and compleat number, is ſufficient to comprehend all of that ranke in that Countrey. This number here being like that, Chap. 9.16. an Army of Horſmen of two hundred thouſand thouſand. Which number comprehends
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:157070:47"/> all thoſe in the Armies, though they were by many degrees ſhort of that huge number, as before. And ſo here.</p>
               <p>It followeth hereupon: That <hi>the remnant were affrighted, and gave glory to the God of Heaven.</hi> The remnant, whether the whole people in that tenth part (as aforeſaid) or whether thoſe that were a kind of Retainers, or favourers, or parties ſiding with the Prelates faction, or altogether, they were ſtruck with feare, as beholding the Almightie power of God in the effecting of that great and admirable work, and thereupon <hi>gave glory to the God of Heaven.</hi> I will conclude this with that of <hi>David:</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 64.7, 8, 9, 10.</note> 
                  <hi>But God ſhall ſhoot at them with an arrow, ſuddainly ſhall they be wounded. So they ſhall make their own tongue to fall upon themſelves: all that ſee them, ſhall flee away. And all men ſhall feare, and ſhall declare the work of God: for they ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſely conſider of his doing. The righteous ſhal be glad in the Lord, and ſhall truſt in him: and all the upright in heart ſhall glory.</hi> Even ſo, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now a word of the next Trumpet, the ſeventh, or laſt. But by the way we find theſe words;<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 14.</note> 
                  <hi>The ſecond woe is paſt: and behold the third woe commeth quickly.</hi> Chap. 18.13. Wee finde three woes, woe, woe, woe. The firſt woe belongeth to the fift Trumpet: as Chapter 9.12. the ſecond woe to the ſixt: and the third woe to the ſeventh. So as the ſixt Trumpet being ended, it is ſaid here, <hi>The ſecond <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oe is paſt:</hi> and the <hi>ſeventh Trumpet</hi> now following, is it added; <hi>And behold the third woe commeth quickly.</hi> That is, the ſeventh Trumpet commeth quickly, bringing its woe with it to the Beaſt and his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:157070:48"/>
               <p>The ſeventh and laſt Trumpet.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 15.</note>
                  <hi>And the ſeventh Angel ſounded, and there were great voices in heaven, ſaying, The Kingdomes of this world are become the Kingdomes of our Lord, and of his Chriſt, and he ſhall reigne for ever and ever, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſeventh Trumpet, as it bringeth woe, even the laſt woe, that is utter ruine and deſtruction to the Beaſt and his Kingdome, to Antichriſt, the Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that great<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ver.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp; Chap.</hi> 17.18.</note> Citie, and to the whole Hierarchie, where ever it be in any part, or Kingdome of the World: ſo it brings great joy and triumph to all the people of God under the Sun. This is that <hi>great voice</hi> from Heaven, yea <hi>great voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> that is, generall acclamations of the whole Church of Chriſt in all places (which is here cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Heaven,</hi> as<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 12.</note> before) Saying, <hi>The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of this world are become the Kingdomes of our Lord,</hi> even of God the <hi>Father, and of his Chriſt, and he ſhal reigne for ever and ever.</hi> That is, when this Trumpet ſhall ſound (which ſhall be quickly, as V. 14.) all the Kingdoms of the World ſhall conſent to the rooting out of Antichriſt and his kingdome, they ſhall caſt downe his Throne which is exalted in and by the Hierarchie, and his whole Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie ſhall they caſt out, and ſhall ſet up Chriſts throne over them; &amp; ſhall ſubject the Kingdoms to Chriſts Government, in ſubmitting and conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Doctrine, &amp; Diſcipline, according to his Word. For till they doe this, ſo long as they up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and take part with the Beaſt, in admitting and mayntaining his Hierarchie in their Dominions, they<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 17.13.</note> 
                  <hi>give their ſtrength and power unto the Beaſt,</hi> and ſubject their Kingdomes unto him, making warre
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:157070:48"/> againſt the <hi>Lambe</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes the while, are not <hi>Chriſts Kingdomes,</hi> but <hi>Antichriſts</hi> rather. A thing well to be conſidered of Chriſtian Kings and Princes, and States. But when this ſeventh Trumpet ſhall ſound (which will bee ſhortly, if not rather already begunne) then is that time fulfilled, which was forelimited of GOD, when they, even the <hi>ten Kings,</hi> to wit, all Chriſtian Kings and States, which before took part with the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> againſt the <hi>Lambe,</hi> even<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 17.16, 17.</note> 
                  <hi>theſe ſhall hate the Whore, and ſhal make her deſolate and naked, and ſhal eat her fleſh, and burn her with fire. For God hath put in their hearts to fulfil his wil, and to agree, and give their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome unto the Beaſt, until the words of God ſhal be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled.</hi> And although this may ſeem ſtrange and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt incredible to mans reaſon and apprehenſion: yet God ſhall as certainly bring it to paſſe, as his Word hath ſaid it. And that we might not be dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident herein, God hath given us a famous and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable inſtance, and as it were a ſenſible taſte hereof, in that late glorious worke of his in the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> (which we noted before) in throwing down that proud Antichriſtian throne of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> which the <hi>Prelates</hi> thought impoſſible to be done, and which ſeemed at firſt but as a<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.1.</note> 
                  <hi>dreame,</hi> even to Gods people, when <hi>the Lord brought againe the captivity of his Sion</hi> in that Land in ſo good a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure begun: whereas now that out-caſt Hierarchie hath as little hope ever to be reſtored, as in their proſperitie they had feare or doubt ever to bee ſo caſt out. Yet wee ſee it with our eyes, that God hath brought to paſſe this great thing. And ſhall we
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:157070:49"/> doubt of the reſt, when he hath given us ſuch a ſure earneſt of his never fayling word, and of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible power? Hee that hath puld off one of the the Beaſts hornes, ſhall ſhortly breake off all his hornes; as the Lord ſaith,<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75.10.</note> 
                  <hi>All the hornes of the wicked alſo will I cut off: but the hornes of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſhall be exalted.</hi> And then, then (I ſay) when the Kingdome of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> that <hi>Whore</hi> (which yet deſperatly triumpheth in the confidence of her ſtately <hi>Babylon,</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 18.7.</note> ſitting in her throne, and <hi>ſaying in her heart, I ſit a Queen, and am no widow,</hi> and ſhall ſee no ſorrow) ſhall bee deſtroyed<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 8.</note> whoſe <hi>plagues ſhal come in one day, death, and mourning, and famine, when ſhe ſhal be utterly burnt with fire; for ſtrong is the Lord who judgeth her:</hi> and ſo, when all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes aforeſaid ſhall reſume their power and ſtrength from the <hi>Beaſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſop <hi>and</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>race.</note> and leave him naked, (as the Birds did the <hi>Crow,</hi> when each bird tooke his owne feather, wherewith the Crow had pranked him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, exalting himſelf above his fellows;) and when they ſhall ſubmit their Scepters unto Jeſus Chriſt, by receiving his government over them, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid: then their Kingdomes become the <hi>Kingdomes of our Lord, and of his Chriſt, and he ſhal reigne for ever and ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But we finde, Chap. 18.9. how the Kings of the earth, who <hi>have committed fornication, and lived deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly with the Whore</hi> of <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſeeing her ruine, ſhall <hi>bewaile her, and lament for her,</hi> &amp;c. and yet Chap. 17. that the <hi>ten hornes,</hi> the <hi>ten Kings, that gave their power and Kingdomes to the Beaſt, ſhal hate the Whore, and make her deſolate and naked, and ſhall eat her fleſh, and burn her with fire.</hi> Theſe two places ſeeme to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:157070:49"/> one another. But being rightly underſtood, there is no contradiction. For firſt, moſt ſure it is, that the <hi>ten Kings</hi> aforeſaid <hi>ſhal hate the Whore,</hi> and be the inſtruments of her deſolation. God will ſurely bring his word to paſſe. But yet ſome of thoſe Kings may at firſt bee brought to it againſt their wils, or with an ill will, having beene formerly ſo much enamoured on the gay painted Whore, and made drunke with the wine of her fornication. We ſee, thoſe two milch-kine of the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> by a ſtrange inſtinct carried Gods Arke to his place, yet lowed all the way after their Calves (1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.) So the Lord will have his work done upon the whore, though ſome of the chiefe inſtruments may have ſtill a yearning of affection after the Whore, for old acquaintance ſake. Yet, though ſome, for their own perſons may doe this for a time, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Whore fals with her goodly <hi>Babylon</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, becauſe the Kings alone ſhall not make <hi>Babylon</hi> deſolate, but their Kingdomes, to wit, their people taken altogether: therefore the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular pitie of ſome for a time ſhall not hinder the generall hatred of the Whore, and ſo <hi>the Kingdomes of this World</hi> mainly and univerſally <hi>ſhal become the Kingdomes of our Lord and of his Chriſt.</hi> And this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king deſolate of the Whore by the Kings and their people, ſhall be with ſuch violence of paſsion, and zeale, which God ſhall kindle in their hearts and breſts, as when it is done, they ſhal ſtand amazed to behold the ſmoke of her burning, and ſpend ſome human compaſſion and pitie upon thoſe terrible and ſuddaine deſolations. Even as <hi>Titus,</hi> that noble <hi>Roman</hi> Generall, when through the obdurate obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacie
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:157070:50"/> of the <hi>Jews</hi> in their extreame miſery, his ſouldiers were ſo enraged, that not only the Citie <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but the moſt beautifull Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple it ſelfe were ſet on fire, hee beholding it, wept over it, to ſee ſuch a goodly and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious building ſo miſerably deſtroyed: the like compaſsion may even thoſe Kings have, in wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping over <hi>Babylon,</hi> when they ſhall behold the ruines thereof, wherein themſelves notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, with their people, were the chief Actors. Thus the ſame Kings, whom the Lord ſhall employ in the making deſolate of <hi>Babylon,</hi> may bee moved with humane compaſsion, when they behold even thoſe ruines, which themſelves by divine inſtigation have made. And as the ſame <hi>Titus,</hi> though hee cryed to his Souldiers to ſave that glorious Monument, the Temple, and not to burn it, and ſeeing it notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all on a flame, cryed out the more vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently to quench it, but could not prevail to reſcue it: So the Kings of the earth, when they ſhall ſee the ſmoke of <hi>Babylons</hi> burning, and ſhall thereupon be moved to lament her, ſaying, <hi>Alas, Alas, that great Citiy</hi> Babylon, <hi>that mighty Citie:</hi> yet ſuch is the Lords fury kindled againſt her, that they ſhall not be able with all their power, though they would never ſo fain, to reſcue her out of the flames. For the Lord will have it ſo; and therefore as <hi>he hath put in their minds to fulfil his wil in giving their ſtrength and Kingdome to the Beaſt, until the words of God be fulfilled:</hi> So, <hi>when the words of God ſhal be fulfilled, he wil alſo put in their minds, to fulfil his wil, in the utter deſtruction of</hi> Babylon. And from this time <hi>Chriſt ſhal reigne for evermore over his people,</hi> when the uſurping Beaſt,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:157070:50"/> with all his power ſhall be put downe, and ſo when all Kings, Princes and States ſhal ſubmit their Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pters to Chriſts authority, as before is ſhewed.</p>
               <p>Then ſhall be great joy, and thankſgiving in the Church, as Verſe 16.17: and in the end of this laſt Trumpet (which how long it ſhall ſound, and the ſounding thereof laſt, he only knows,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 1.7. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24 36.</note> who hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved it in his owne breſt) ſhall come the generall judgement of quick and dead, wherein God ſhall powre wrath upon his wrathfull enemies, and ſhall reward all his faithful ſervants, as Verſe 18. Now there be ſundry other things very myſticall and darke, which ſeeme to come under the time of this laſt Trumpet, as (beſides the remainder of this Chapter, Verſe 19. which gives ſome light of the generall converſion of the <hi>Jewes</hi>) the whole twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth Chapter of this Booke: but becauſe they be very obſcure, and will require longer time and ſtronger Prayers for aſsiſting and illuminating grace in the opening of them: therefore I will here put an end for the preſent, till it ſhall pleaſe God to give a further opportunitie. In the mean time,<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.17.</note> 
                  <hi>We give thee thanks, O Lord God Almighty, which art and waſt, and art to come, becauſe thou haſt taken to thee thy great power, and haſt reigned. Even ſo,</hi> AMEN.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
